<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
    <info>
        <title>Framework for Method Ringing - False Courseheads</title>
        <othermeta>source=version2\falsecourseheads.html</othermeta>
    </info>
    <section>
        <para>Framework for Method Ringing     
[Switch version]</para>
        <para>1. Introduction
2. Versioning
3. Fundamentals of Method Ringing
4. Method Classification
5. Method Naming
6. Performance Reporting
7. Record Lengths
8. Method Extension
9. Related Roles
    Appendices
A. Place Notation
B. Method Name Syntax
C. Leadhead Codes
D. Extension Processes
E. False Courseheads
F. Framework Principles
G. Version 2 Development
H. Version 2 Consultation
Appendix E. False Courseheads
                            1.
                                This appendix shows groupings of false courseheads.
                                It is possible for one course of a method to contain one or more rows that also appear in another course of the same method.
                                For example, the course of Cambridge Surprise Major that starts with 13245678 (which is referred to as this course's coursehead) contains
                                the row 12345678 after the 2nd change of the 5th lead.
                                The course with coursehead 13245678 is therefore false against the plain course.
                                Furthermore, it can be shown that courses that are false against a reference course (which is usually taken to be the plain course)
                                occur in groups that are consistent across methods of the same type, such as methods with Plain Bob leadheads and one hunt bell,
                                where the hunt bells have the same path.
                                The table below shows the falseness groupings of the 120 courses that comprise all the possible orderings of bells 2 to 6.
                                These groupings apply to palindromic methods with an even stage of 8 or higher, with Plain Bob leadheads,
                                and with a single hunt bell that follows a Treble Dodging path.
                                As the table only considers the possible orderings of bells 2 - 6 (the working bells), the remaining bells (the fixed bells) are removed
                                from the table for conciseness. The treble (i.e. the hunt bell) is also removed.
                                For example, coursehead 34265 is referring to 13426578 when considering Major, 1342657890 when considering Royal, and so on.
                                The table below is divided into courseheads that are "in-course" and courseheads that are "out-of-course".
                                In-course courses are those that can be reached with bobs only (place notation 14 or 1[n-2]) when starting from rounds.
                                Out-of-course courses are those that can only be reached with bobs plus an odd number of singles (1234 or 1[n-2][n-1][n])
                                when starting from rounds.
                                False coursehead groups that are designated below by uppercase letters A to U contain in-course false courseheads,
                                and may also contain out-of-course false courseheads.
                                Groups designated by lowercase letters a to f contain only out-of-course false courseheads.
                                Groups A to U and a to f also include tenors-split members that are not shown in these
                                tables. There are 3 additional groups, X, Y and Z, that only have tenors-split
                                members and do not have any tenors-together members. As these tables only show
                                tenors-together members, groups X, Y and Z show below as not having any members.
                            2.
                                    Group code
                                    A
                                    B
                                    C
                                    D
                                    E
                                    F
                                    G
                                    H
                                    I
                                    K
                                    L
                                    In-course
                                    23456
                                    24365
                                    25634
                                    32546
                                    46253
                                    32465
                                    43265
                                    45236
                                    32654
                                    56423
                                    63542
                                    53462
                                    63425
                                    54632
                                    65324
                                    65432
                                    53624
                                    26543 ) L1
                                    42563 ) L2
                                    36245 )
                                    Out-of-course
                                    [None]
                                    25436
                                    32456
                                    23654
                                    43256
                                    42365
                                    34265
                                    53426
                                    63452
                                    24356
                                    25364
                                    24635
                                    26345
                                    24563
                                    [None]
                                    56243
                                    62543
                                    46523
                                    36542
                                    [None]
                                    46352 ) K1
                                    52346 )
                                    64253 )
                                    34526 )
                                    64325 ) K2
                                    54362 )
                                    [None]
                                    Group code
                                    M
                                    N
                                    O
                                    P
                                    R
                                    S
                                    T
                                    U
                                    In-course
                                    23564
                                    23645
                                    25463
                                    26435
                                    34562
                                    62345
                                    46325
                                    54263
                                    52643
                                    36524
                                    65243
                                    46532
                                    54326 ) P1
                                    64352 )
                                    56342 ) P2
                                    64523 )
                                    45623
                                    56234
                                    35642
                                    62534
                                    52364
                                    34625
                                    64235
                                    45362
                                    24536
                                    25346
                                    36452
                                    43526
                                    62453
                                    26354
                                    53246
                                    24653
                                    34256 ) U1
                                    42356 )
                                    43652 )
                                    63254 )
                                    52436 )
                                    35426 )
                                    35264 ) U2
                                    42635 )
                                    Out-of-course
                                    [None]
                                    62435 ) N1
                                    53264 )
                                    43625 )
                                    35462 )
                                    65234 ) N2
                                    45632 )
                                    52634 )
                                    35624 )
                                    63524
                                    53642
                                    56432
                                    65423
                                    [None]
                                    [None]
                                    [None]
                                    32564
                                    32645
                                    46235
                                    45263
                                    [None]
                                    Group code
                                    a
                                    b
                                    c
                                    d
                                    e
                                    f
                                    In-course
                                    [None]
                                    [None]
                                    [None]
                                    [None]
                                    [None]
                                    [None]
                                    Out-of-course
                                    23465 ) a1
                                    23546 ) a2
                                    26453 )
                                    26534
                                    25643
                                    35246
                                    42536
                                    42653
                                    36254
                                    34652
                                    45326
                                    62354
                                    54236
                                    36425
                                    52463
                                    43562
                                    63245
                                    54623
                                    56324
                                    65342
                                    64532
                                    Group code
                                    X
                                    Y
                                    Z
                                    In-course
                                    [None]
                                    [None]
                                    [None]
                                    Out-of-course
                                    [None]
                                    [None]
                                    [None]
                            3.
                                In Major, groups that include both in-course and out-of-course false courseheads always occur as complete groups.
                                However, in Royal and above, in-course and out-of-course components of a group may occur independently.
                                Therefore in the Methods Library, in-course and out-of-course groups are shown separated by a "/" for Royal and higher.
                                For example, E/Bc indicates that the in-course false courseheads of group E, and the out-of-course false courseheads of groups B and c
                                apply to the method (Royal or higher) in question.
                                A further consideration in Royal and higher is that certain of the groups defined above, K, L, N, P, U and a, can subdivide.
                                The subdivisions, indicated by K1, K2, L1, L2, N1, N2, P1, P2, U1, U2, and a1, a2 are also shown in the table above.
                                A Royal or higher method might therefore include U1 rather than U before the "/", or N2 rather than N after the "/".
                            4.
Example: Ibstock Surprise Royal has the following in the Methods Library:
                                    FCHs
                                    Ibstock
                                    L1/BDK1c
                                The false courseheads associated with Ibstock are accordingly:
                                In-course: 26543
                                Out-of-course: 25436, 32456, 23654, 43256, 53426, 63452, 24356, 46352, 52346, 64253, 34526, 35246, 42536, 42653, 36254
                            5.
Example: A composition might be advertised as being 'true to BDEKacdefYZ'.
                                A band is considering using this composition to ring Othorpe Surprise Major.
                                The CC Methods Library shows that the false coursehead groups for Othorpe are BDXY.
                                Because Othorpe has group X falseness but the composition does not include X in the list
                                of groups that it is true to, this composition will be false if used with Othorpe.
                            6.
                                Methods without any in-course false courseheads are referred to as "cps", or clear proof scale.
                                However, these methods will usually have out-of-course false courseheads.
                                Bristol Surprise Major is an example of a cps method.
                            7.
                                A method that is false in the plain course will have false coursehead group A, usually in addition to other groups.</para>
    </section>
</article>
