<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Framework for Method Ringing - Fundamentals of Method Ringing
  Version 2.0 (Definitive)
  Authority: Central Council of Church Bell Ringers (CCCBR)

  Schema: DocBook 5.0 (http://docbook.org/ns/docbook)
  Custom namespace mrf: for domain-specific metadata attributes.

  Structure:
    article                 - one file per chapter/page of the framework
      info                  - document-level metadata (version, status, authority)
      glossary              - the body of definitions
        glossdiv            - a lettered section (A. Stages, B. Rows, ...)
          glossentry        - a numbered term definition
            glossterm       - the term being defined
            glossdef        - the definition and supplementary content
              para          - definition text
              example       - worked example
              note role="further-explanation"   - explanatory text
              note role="technical-comment"     - technical/mathematical remarks

  Formatting conventions:
    - 2-space indent for nested elements
    - Block elements (para, note, example, glossentry, glossdef, ...) on their own line
    - Inline elements (emphasis, link, literal, ...) may remain on the same line as text
    - No significant whitespace inside para/emphasis/link content

  Version support:
    The mrf:status attribute on article controls discovery priority:
      definitive  - current approved version (boost in search / LLM context)
      draft       - candidate next version
      historic    - superseded version
-->
<article
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:mrf="https://cccbr.org.uk/ns/method-ringing-framework"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="fundamentals-v2"
  xml:lang="en"
  mrf:status="definitive"
  mrf:authority="CCCBR"
  mrf:framework-version="2.0">

  <info>
    <title>Fundamentals of Method Ringing</title>
    <subtitle>Framework for Method Ringing, Section 3</subtitle>
    <edition>2.0</edition>
    <releaseinfo role="status">definitive</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="authority">CCCBR</releaseinfo>
    <uri type="canonical">https://cccbr.github.io/method_ringing_framework/version2/fundamentals.html</uri>
  </info>

  <glossary>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <!-- A. Stages                                                     -->
    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <glossdiv xml:id="stages">
      <title>A. Stages</title>

      <glossentry xml:id="term-stage" mrf:number="A.1" mrf:status="definitive">
        <glossterm>Stage</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
          <para>A property of several method ringing concepts that indicates the number of bells participating.</para>
          <note role="further-explanation">
            <para>Stage applies to the following method ringing concepts: Rows, Changes, Blocks, Methods and Compositions.</para>
            <para>The application of Stage to each of these concepts will be covered below in the
              <quote>Further explanation</quote> sections of the definitions of these concepts.
              In addition, see <link xlink:href="images/fundamentals/understanding-stage.pdf">Understanding Stage</link>
              for an overview of all aspects of Stage.</para>
          </note>
        </glossdef>
      </glossentry>

      <glossentry xml:id="term-stage-name" mrf:number="A.2" mrf:status="definitive">
        <glossterm>Stage Name</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
          <para>Names that are given to the different Stages, as follows:</para>
          <para>1 = One; 3 = Singles; 5 = Doubles; 7 = Triples; 9 = Caters; 11 = Cinques;
            13 = Sextuples; 15 = Septuples; 17 = Octuples.</para>
          <para>2 = Two; 4 = Minimus; 6 = Minor; 8 = Major; 10 = Royal; 12 = Maximus;
            14 = Fourteen; 16 = Sixteen; 18 = Eighteen.</para>
          <para>Odd and even Stages above 18 are named with the written form of the corresponding
            Stage number, such as Nineteen and Twenty-Two.</para>
        </glossdef>
      </glossentry>

    </glossdiv>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <!-- B. Rows                                                       -->
    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <glossdiv xml:id="rows">
      <title>B. Rows</title>

      <glossentry xml:id="term-row" mrf:number="B.1" mrf:status="definitive">
        <glossterm>Row</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
          <para>A sequence of numbered bells in which no bell appears more than once.
            The bells are numbered consecutively, starting from number one.</para>
          <example>
            <para>531246 is a Row with a Stage of Minor (or equivalently, a Minor Row).</para>
          </example>
          <note role="further-explanation">
            <para>The Stage of a Row is the number of bells in that Row.
              See <link xlink:href="images/fundamentals/understanding-stage.pdf">Understanding Stage</link>
              for an overview of all aspects of Stage.</para>
            <para>Bells are usually numbered in descending order of pitch.
              Both cardinal numbers (e.g. 1, 2, 3 ...) and ordinal numbers (e.g. 1st, 2nd, 3rd ...) are used.
              When using cardinals, number 1 is used for the bell with the highest pitch, number 2 for the next
              highest pitch and so on. When using ordinals, bell number 2 becomes <quote>the 2nd</quote>,
              bell number 3 becomes <quote>the 3rd</quote>, and so on. However, bell number 1 is usually referred
              to as <quote>the treble</quote> rather than <quote>the 1st</quote>, and the bell with the lowest
              pitch is usually referred to as <quote>the tenor</quote> rather than the corresponding ordinal.</para>
            <para>Bells are numbered relative to how many are in use. For example, if a tower has eight bells
              but only the six with the lowest pitches are in use, these bells are numbered 1 to 6 instead
              of 3 to 8.</para>
            <para>Rows are normally shown in columns so that the path of individual bells can be visualised
              by looking down the columns. In order to keep the columns aligned, a fixed font can be used with
              single characters representing each bell. Conventionally <literal>0</literal> (zero) is used to
              represent the 10th, and upper case letters (excluding I, O and X) are used for bells 11 to 33
              as follows: E (Eleven); T (Twelve); A (Thirteen); B (Fourteen); C (Fifteen); D (Sixteen);
              F (Seventeen); G (Eighteen); H (Nineteen); J (Twenty); K (Twenty-one); L (Twenty-two);
              M (Twenty-three); N (Twenty-four); P (Twenty-five); Q (Twenty-six); R (Twenty-seven);
              S (Twenty-eight); U (Twenty-nine); V (Thirty); W (Thirty-one); Y (Thirty-two);
              Z (Thirty-three).</para>
            <para>Note that what is defined as a Row in this section is sometimes described as a Change in
              common ringing parlance. The Framework separately uses Change as the transition between two Rows
              (see Section C). Row is the preferred term wherever possible.</para>
          </note>
          <note role="technical-comment">
            <para>While this definition of Row refers to a sequence of <emphasis role="italic">bells</emphasis>,
              a Row can comprise, at minimum, one bell.</para>
          </note>
        </glossdef>
      </glossentry>

      <glossentry xml:id="term-rounds" mrf:number="B.2" mrf:status="definitive">
        <glossterm>Rounds</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
          <para>A Row in which the bells are ordered from the lowest number to the highest number.</para>
          <example>
            <para>12345678 is Rounds for a Major Row.</para>
          </example>
        </glossdef>
      </glossentry>

      <glossentry xml:id="term-place" mrf:number="B.3" mrf:status="definitive">
        <glossterm>Place</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
          <para>The position of a bell within a Row.</para>
          <example>
            <para>In the Row 142536, the 2nd bell is in 3rd's Place.</para>
          </example>
          <note role="further-explanation">
            <para>Places are numbered starting with 1 for the first bell in the Row, and increasing
              sequentially for each next bell in the Row. E.g. the bell that is second in a Row is in Place 2.</para>
            <para>Each bell in a Row appears in a different Place to all other bells in that Row, and therefore
              there are the same number of Places in a Row as there are bells in that Row.</para>
            <para>Places are often referred to using ordinal numbers in the possessive form, so Place 2 is often
              <quote>2nd's Place</quote>. 2nd's Place is a reference to the Place the 2nd bell occupies
              in Rounds.</para>
            <para>The bell in 1st's Place is often said to be <emphasis role="italic">leading</emphasis>, and
              the bell in the last Place of the Row is often said to be <emphasis role="italic">lying</emphasis>.
              E.g. in the Row 214365, the 2nd is leading and the 5th is lying.</para>
          </note>
        </glossdef>
      </glossentry>

    </glossdiv>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <!-- C. Changes                                                    -->
    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <glossdiv xml:id="changes">
      <title>C. Changes</title>

      <glossentry xml:id="term-change" mrf:number="C.1" mrf:status="definitive">
        <glossterm>Change</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
          <para>A transposition of bells from an existing Row to a new Row, where both Rows have the same Stage.</para>
          <example>
            <para>A Change might transpose the bells from the Row 214365 to the Row 241356.</para>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/fundamentals/change.svg" width="300px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </example>
          <note role="further-explanation">
            <para>The Stage of a Change is the number of bells on which that Change operates.
              See <link xlink:href="images/fundamentals/understanding-stage.pdf">Understanding Stage</link>
              for an overview of all aspects of Stage.</para>
            <para>Since a Change is a transposition of bells, the new Row will comprise the same set of
              bells as the existing Row.</para>
            <para>Note that the same Change applied to different Rows will have the same relative effect.
              For example, a Change applied to the Row 1342 might produce the Row 1432. The same Change
              applied to the Row 4123 would produce the Row 4213.</para>
          </note>
          <note role="technical-comment">
            <para>Note that in mathematics, transposition refers to the exchange of two elements. However in
              ringing, as well as in more general usage, transposition can involve the exchange of more than
              two elements. For example, ringers talk about transposing coursing orders, which often involves
              rotating 3 bells.</para>
          </note>
        </glossdef>
      </glossentry>

      <glossentry xml:id="term-identity-change" mrf:number="C.2" mrf:status="definitive">
        <glossterm>Identity Change</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
          <para>A Change that transposes each bell to the same Place in a new Row.</para>
          <example>
            <para>The Change that transposes the bells from Row 54321 to Row 54321 is an Identity Change.</para>
          </example>
        </glossdef>
      </glossentry>

      <glossentry xml:id="term-adjacent-change" mrf:number="C.3" mrf:status="definitive">
        <glossterm>Adjacent Change</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
          <para>A Change that transposes each bell to either the same Place or an adjacent Place in a new Row,
            but which is not an Identity Change.</para>
          <example>
            <para>The Change that transposes the bells from Row 21436587 to Row 12346857 is an Adjacent Change.</para>
          </example>
          <note role="technical-comment">
            <para>An Adjacent Change has a minimum Stage of 2.</para>
          </note>
        </glossdef>
      </glossentry>

      <glossentry xml:id="term-jump-change" mrf:number="C.4" mrf:status="definitive">
        <glossterm>Jump Change</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
          <para>A Change that transposes at least one bell to a different and non-adjacent Place in a new Row.</para>
          <example>
            <para>The Change that transposes the bells from Row 12345678 to Row 23415678 is a Jump Change
              because the treble moves from 1st's Place to 4th's Place, which are not adjacent Places.</para>
          </example>
          <note role="further-explanation">
            <para>When ringing heavy bells, Jump Changes are more commonly used to jump from an earlier Place
              to a later Place, rather than vice versa, due to the physical difficulty of reducing the time
              between bell strikes.</para>
          </note>
          <note role="technical-comment">
            <para>A Jump Change has a minimum Stage of 3.</para>
          </note>
        </glossdef>
      </glossentry>

    </glossdiv>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <!-- D. Blocks  (opening entry only — pattern continues)          -->
    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <glossdiv xml:id="blocks">
      <title>D. Blocks</title>

      <glossentry xml:id="term-block" mrf:number="D.1" mrf:status="definitive">
        <glossterm>Block</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
          <para>A sequence of Changes, all with the same Stage, and the Rows produced by applying these
            Changes, starting from an initial Row.</para>
          <example>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/fundamentals/block.svg" width="250px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </example>
          <note role="further-explanation">
            <para>The Stage of the Changes in the sequence is the same as the Stage of the initial Row.
              A Block has the Stage of its constituent Rows.
              See <link xlink:href="images/fundamentals/understanding-stage.pdf">Understanding Stage</link>
              for an overview of all aspects of Stage.</para>
            <para>A sequence of Changes is used to produce a sequence of Rows as follows:
              apply the first Change to an initial Row to produce a second Row;
              apply the second Change to the second Row to produce a third Row; and so on.
              The Row produced by applying the final Change is referred to as the final Row.</para>
            <para>Since a Block is generated using Changes, which are transpositions of bells, all Rows
              in a Block will comprise the same set of bells.</para>
            <para>Note that a Block always has one more Row than it has Changes.</para>
            <para>See Section E.1 (Method) for an explanation of the difference between a Method and a Block.</para>
            <para>Dividing lines are often drawn in Blocks to highlight features — they have no effect
              on the Rows produced.</para>
            <para>The following diagram shows the relationships between the various components of method ringing.
              Terms in the diagram that are not defined above are defined elsewhere in the Framework.</para>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/fundamentals/hierarchy.svg" width="100%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </note>
          <note role="technical-comment">
            <para>The term Block is also used in method ringing to refer to a sequence of Changes without
              reference to the Rows they can produce. For example, a Composition may specify a Block of
              Changes that is repeated at different points. While the Framework uses Block to mean both
              Changes and the Rows produced, this does not preclude its use in the narrower sense elsewhere.</para>
            <para>A Block has a minimum size of one Change and two Rows.</para>
          </note>
        </glossdef>
      </glossentry>

    </glossdiv>

    <!-- Further glossdiv sections (E. Methods through K. Performances) follow the same pattern -->

  </glossary>

</article>
