<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mrf="https://cccbr.org.uk/ns/method-ringing-framework" version="5.0" xml:id="consultation-v1" xml:lang="en" mrf:status="historic" mrf:authority="CCCBR" mrf:framework-version="1" mrf:edition-label="Edition 1">
  <info>
    <title>Consultation</title>
    <subtitle>Framework for Method Ringing, Appendix H</subtitle>
    <edition>1</edition>
    <releaseinfo role="status">historic</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="authority">CCCBR</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="implementation-date">February 24, 2019</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="effective-date">June 1, 2019</releaseinfo>
    <uri type="canonical">https://cccbr.org.uk/consultation.html</uri>
    <othermeta role="source-path">version1/consultation.html</othermeta>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="section-2">
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>The first ringing-community-wide consultation on the framework started on Fri May 18th 2018 and ended on Fri Sep 21st 2018. A Ringing World article published on May 18th 2018 explained the first consultation process. This article is available as item 4 in Appendix G of this website (Related Material).</para>
        <para>35 submissions were received in the first consultation. The points raised, and the framework team's responses to them, are documented in the FAQs in Appendix I, Sections A to L. Over 70 points were raised, and these led to over 30 <nolink>changes</nolink> to the framework.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The second ringing-community-wide consultation on the framework started on Fri Oct 26th 2018 and ended on Fri Nov 30th 2018. A Ringing World article published on Oct 26th 2018 explained the second consultation process. This article is available as item 7 in Appendix G of this website (Related Material).</para>
        <para>9 submissions were received in the second consultation. The points raised, and the framework team's responses to them, are documented in the FAQs in Appendix I, Section M. Over 60 points were raised, and these led to around 25 <nolink>changes</nolink> to the framework.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In total, over 40 ringers contributed to either or both of the consultations. Thanks to everyone who provided feedback -- this resulted in many improvements to the framework.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</article>
