<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mrf="https://cccbr.org.uk/ns/method-ringing-framework" version="5.0" xml:id="faqs-v1" xml:lang="en" mrf:status="historic" mrf:authority="CCCBR" mrf:framework-version="1" mrf:edition-label="Edition 1">
  <info>
    <title>FAQs</title>
    <subtitle>Framework for Method Ringing, Appendix I</subtitle>
    <edition>1</edition>
    <releaseinfo role="status">historic</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="authority">CCCBR</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="implementation-date">February 24, 2019</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="effective-date">June 1, 2019</releaseinfo>
    <uri type="canonical">https://cccbr.org.uk/faqs.html</uri>
    <othermeta role="source-path">version1/faqs.html</othermeta>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="section-2">
    <para>This page provides responses to questions and points that were raised via the consultation on the new framework. The submissions below have been edited for brevity and clarity in a standalone format.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="methodclassification">
    <title>A. Method Classification</title>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem mrf:label="1.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">In classification alternative B, does there need to be something about more than one <nolink>hunt bell</nolink>, as there is in alternative A?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Handling of additional <nolink>hunt bells</nolink> isn't needed in Alternative B because this alternative always classifies a <nolink>hunter</nolink> based on the <nolink>path</nolink> of the treble bell, regardless of how many <nolink>hunt bells</nolink> there are. This is viewed as aligning more closely with the historic terms used -- e.g. treble bob, treble <nolink>dodging</nolink> and treble <nolink>place</nolink>. However this is now a moot point as the classification system we've moved to (which can be viewed as somewhere between Alternatives A and B) applies the hierarchical approach to <nolink>hunt</nolink>
            <nolink>paths</nolink> that is used in Alternative A.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="2.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">It was hard to compare classification alternatives A and B. Could they be presented side by side, or the differences described point by point?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Agree they weren't easy to compare as presented -- apologies for that. As noted in our Oct 26th 2018 RW article (see Appendix G.7), we've now settled on a classification system that can be viewed as falling somewhere between Alt A and Alt B, and is the single classification section now included in this website.</para>
          <para>However, we do plan to put together a table that compares the classifications used in the Decisions, Alt A, Alt B, and the final classification system used in the framework. We'll update this FAQ with a link to the classification comparison table when ready.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="3.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I couldn't locate the list of <nolink>methods</nolink> whose titles would <nolink>change</nolink> under classification Alt B.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Yes, apologies that this wasn't as easily located as it could have been. It's part of the Transitional Arrangements page -- see Appendix F.1. We've now also included a reference to this list in the further explanation of Section 4.A.1. Note that this list now shows the <nolink>changes</nolink> under the updated classification system included in this website, rather than the previous Alt B.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="clarity">
    <title>B. Clarity</title>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem mrf:label="1.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Somehow the term '<nolink>hunter</nolink>' feels wrong, and if it is already in use I've not heard it before. If it is not in use then what is wrong with simply Hunt, or Hunt Method, which would then be consistent with Jump Method? (I presume you considered Jumper.)</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>The term '<nolink>hunter</nolink>' is fairly recent - it was introduced in 2002 as part of the update to the Decisions that introduced <nolink>differential</nolink>
            <nolink>hunters</nolink>. We debated whether to use '<nolink>hunt</nolink>
            <nolink>method</nolink>' instead of '<nolink>hunter</nolink>', and possibly also '<nolink>differential</nolink>
            <nolink>method</nolink>' instead of '<nolink>differential</nolink>'. But the one-word versions are useful (e.g. when wanting conciseness on a web page) so the consensus was to keep '<nolink>hunter</nolink>' and '<nolink>differential</nolink>'. But we drew the line at 'jumper', given its other meanings.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="2.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Is the definition of Hunting correct (see Section 4.A.7)? Wouldn't this result in a point at the extremities of the <nolink>rows</nolink>, rather than a <nolink>place</nolink>?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We intend Hunting, as a standalone term, to mean <nolink>hunting</nolink> in a single direction (i.e. either <nolink>hunting</nolink> up or <nolink>hunting</nolink> down). The main use of <nolink>hunting</nolink> is in the definition of a Place method, in which the <nolink>paths</nolink> of all the bells consist only of Hunting and Making Places.</para>
          <para>This is distinct from a Plain Hunt Path (or Plain Hunting Path), which consists of <nolink>hunting</nolink> up, making a <nolink>place</nolink>, <nolink>hunting</nolink> down and making another <nolink>place</nolink>. While Plain Hunt Path isn't a term we needed to define for use elsewhere, we've now included this term in the further explanation of the Plain Method class definition (see Section 4.D.1).</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="3.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">How about a picture of a lead of a <nolink>method</nolink> with Leadend, Leadhead, Halflead, etc highlighted? Same with <nolink>dodging places</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Good suggestions -- a diagram showing the Leadend, Leadhead, Halflead Change and Leadend Change has now been added (see Section 4.A.12). A diagram showing <nolink>dodging places</nolink> has also been added (see Section 4.A.15).</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="4.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">There seems to be a tendency in ringing and in business to introduce a new vocabulary which the older practitioners find difficult to understand, so perhaps a glossary of terms might be given somewhere. Reports of <nolink>peals</nolink> in the RW now refer to cyclical and particles and it would be helpful to the rank and file ringers if these terms could be explained.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>The framework does define the ringing terms it uses as they are introduced. However, we've only defined the terms that are needed across the framework. We don't view the framework as the right <nolink>place</nolink> to house an extensive glossary of ringing terms -- this would turn an already-complex document into an even more complex one. However an extensive glossary of ringing terms already exists <link xlink:href="http://jaharrison.me.uk/Ringing/Glossary">here</link>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="5.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">There appears to be a pretty much random use of capital letters inconsistent with the conventional use of English.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Words have been capitalised in the framework where they are specialist ringing terms that are defined elsewhere in the framework. This was previously noted in Section 2, which has become Appendix E, so we've now added this note to Section 1 to make it more prominent. A better approach might be to italicise the words rather than capitalise them, and make them hyperlinks to the definitions in question (which also gives the option of presenting them underlined or in a different color). There is various scope overall for improving the appearance of the framework website -- this is on the list of items to consider for a subsequent version of the framework, including how best to highlight defined terms.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="6.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I note the term Identity change -- why not use Identical?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Identity was chosen because it's used in mathematics to denote an operation that, when applied to an input, produces an output that is the same as the input. E.g. the identity for addition is zero, because n + 0 = n. In <nolink>change</nolink> ringing, we apply a <nolink>change</nolink> to a <nolink>row</nolink> in order to produce a new <nolink>row</nolink>, so it's consistent to <nolink>call</nolink> the <nolink>change</nolink> that results in a new <nolink>row</nolink> that's the same as the previous <nolink>row</nolink> the <nolink>identity change</nolink>. 'Null <nolink>change</nolink>' has also been used in the past for the <nolink>identity change</nolink>. A discussion about this in the ringing-theory email group indicated a preference for identity over null.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="7.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">In section 2C you use 'Length' &amp; 'Stage' as defined terms but they have not yet been defined above. I understand them but the majority of my local <nolink>band</nolink> wouldn’t.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Agreed. To give a better structure to the framework, we've now moved the former Section 2 to Appendix E (Framework Development). This also solves the ordering issue that you raise.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I’m not sure the layman would understand the difference in the definitions of Block &amp; Method. The further explanation helps but the actual definition is almost identical.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>The are various terms in <nolink>method</nolink> ringing that have similar meanings (e.g. <nolink>touch</nolink> and <nolink>composition</nolink>), as well as terms that have more than one meaning (e.g. lead can refer to ringing in 1st's <nolink>place</nolink> or a lead of a <nolink>method</nolink>). We've tried to distinguish similar terms as best we can: We view a <nolink>method</nolink> as just the sequence of <nolink>changes</nolink>, without considering the <nolink>rows</nolink> that the <nolink>method</nolink> can be used to generate.</para>
          <para>A <nolink>block</nolink>, on the other hand, results from applying a sequence of <nolink>changes</nolink> (i.e. a <nolink>method</nolink> or a <nolink>composition</nolink>) to a starting <nolink>row</nolink> (normally <nolink>rounds</nolink>). A <nolink>block</nolink> therefore comprises a set of <nolink>rows</nolink> and the <nolink>changes</nolink> used to generate them.</para>
          <para>A <nolink>method</nolink> can be viewed as the process, and a <nolink>block</nolink> as the result of the process.</para>
          <para>Related to these terms, a <nolink>touch</nolink> is a <nolink>block</nolink> generated by a <nolink>composition</nolink>, and a <nolink>plain lead</nolink> and a <nolink>plain course</nolink> are <nolink>blocks</nolink> generated by a single <nolink>method</nolink> without any <nolink>calls</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Pictures would help the understanding of the symmetry definitions (section 4.B).</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Good suggestion. These have now been added. See Section 4.B.3.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="10.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Have a much simpler section which explains standard <nolink>method</nolink> ringing so that ordinary ringers can see how to talk and write about what they do. Then put all the strange exotic stuff at the back. This document is too long and complex for any ordinary ringer to read, and not sufficiently precise, nor using the right mathematical terms, to be usefully referenced from a mathematical paper.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We considered this, but the difficulty is that there will be lots of different views on where to draw the line between vanilla and exotic. This approach could also make it harder for readers to find the information they're looking for.</para>
          <para>Also, the framework exists to be able to describe all <nolink>method</nolink> ringing and is not intended as an introductory primer to <nolink>method</nolink> ringing -- there are other publications that provide this.</para>
          <para>The framework is also intentionally not a mathematical paper. Although not an introductory primer, it should be accessible to as many ringers as possible. However, we are considering adding a new section to a subsequent version of the framework that describes <nolink>method</nolink> ringing in mathematical terms (with development of this led by a ringing mathematician). This could then by used by mathematicians -- e.g. to reference in an academic paper.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="11.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I was unclear about the use of <nolink>stage</nolink> at various points in the framework. There seem to be requirements of various terms to be all 'of the same <nolink>stage</nolink>' which did not make sense to my mind as it precluded <nolink>blocks</nolink>/<nolink>compositions</nolink> of <nolink>spliced</nolink> triples and major (given the commonplace understanding of the term '<nolink>stage</nolink>'). However, an explanation is found hidden away in explanatory notes for <nolink>cover bells</nolink>. I think that something should be done to enable a clearer understanding of this concept in the main text, especially as various sections of the explanatory notes relate; not everything is one <nolink>place</nolink>. (I also do not understand why Plain Bob Doubles/Plain Bob Minor rung side by side on 12 produces Maximus <nolink>changes</nolink> as there are 11 bells affected by the <nolink>method</nolink> – so surely this would be cinques <nolink>changes</nolink> as per the example given elsewhere of Plain Bob Minor/Plain Bob Cinques rung side by side).</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>A few people commented that the use of '<nolink>stage</nolink>' in the framework wasn't clear, and/or that the information on '<nolink>stage</nolink>' is too fragmented across the framework.</para>
          <para>Because <nolink>stage</nolink> is a concept that applies to various other concepts (<nolink>rows</nolink>, <nolink>changes</nolink>, <nolink>blocks</nolink>, <nolink>methods</nolink> and <nolink>compositions</nolink>), organising the information can become circular (e.g. the definition of <nolink>method</nolink> involves <nolink>stage</nolink>, but defining <nolink>stage</nolink> without referring to a <nolink>method</nolink> can be too abstract). To address this, we've created a short document that covers all aspects of <nolink>stage</nolink> in one <nolink>place</nolink>. The framework now links to this document wherever <nolink>stage</nolink> is defined, i.e. in the definition of Row (3.B.1), Change (3.C.1), Block (3.D.1), Method (3.E.1), Composition (3.G.1) and Cover Bell (3.H.1), as well as in the initial definition of Stage itself (3.A.1).</para>
          <para>On the question about Doubles / Minor rung side by side on 12 bells, this would indeed normally result in Cinques <nolink>changes</nolink>, which could then be rung (say) with the 12th as a <nolink>cover bell</nolink>. But in the example in the technical comment of 3.H.1, the Doubles is being rung on bells 1-5, and the Minor is being ruing on bells 7-12, with 6th's <nolink>place</nolink> containing a <nolink>cover bell</nolink>. For practical purposes (e.g. when entering <nolink>changes</nolink> into a proving program), the <nolink>changes</nolink> would most likely be specified as Maximus <nolink>changes</nolink>, with a place notation of '6' included in every <nolink>change</nolink>. But the <nolink>effective stage</nolink> of the <nolink>block</nolink> produced by these <nolink>changes</nolink> would still be Cinques (assuming there are no other <nolink>fixed places</nolink>).</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="12.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.J.4 states that the final <nolink>row</nolink> should be excluded in calculating <nolink>truth</nolink> in a <nolink>round block</nolink>. I wondered if it should be the 1st <nolink>row</nolink> as if you start a <nolink>touch</nolink> in <nolink>rounds</nolink>, the first <nolink>change</nolink> takes you to the first non-<nolink>rounds</nolink>
              <nolink>touch</nolink> of the <nolink>composition</nolink>; therefore is the initial <nolink>row</nolink> really part of the <nolink>composition</nolink>? There are probably good reasons, however, why this is not the case which I have not appreciated.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We had quite a lengthy debate on this point when drafting the framework. The reality is that when determining the <nolink>truth</nolink> of a <nolink>round block</nolink>, you can exclude either the initial <nolink>row</nolink> or the final <nolink>row</nolink> (these two <nolink>rows</nolink> being the same). We felt that using either/or language throughout the framework would be a little cumbersome, so decided to standardise on including the initial <nolink>row</nolink> and excluding the final <nolink>row</nolink>. This approach often aligns with the symmetry of what is being rung, and also, in <nolink>spliced</nolink>
            <nolink>compositions</nolink>, the atw (all-the-work) property is determined based on a lead starting with the <nolink>leadhead</nolink> and finishing with the <nolink>leadend</nolink>, rather than one <nolink>row</nolink> later (this avoids possible missed <nolink>rows</nolink> due to <nolink>calls</nolink>). But in practice the other approach will also be useful. E.g. when judging a striking competition, if the rules <nolink>call</nolink> for not judging the opening and closing <nolink>rounds</nolink>, the judge probably won't know the <nolink>touch</nolink> has started until she hears a non-<nolink>rounds</nolink>
            <nolink>row</nolink>. So in this scenario, it would make sense to exclude the initial <nolink>row</nolink> and include the final <nolink>row</nolink> for judging purposes.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="13.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I felt that 3.K.3 was a little ambiguous in the term 'same set of Methods'. I assume this means a <nolink>record lengths</nolink> for <nolink>spliced</nolink>. I am unclear at what level the set of <nolink>methods</nolink> is defined, <nolink>stage</nolink>, or <nolink>stage</nolink> and <nolink>method class</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Yes, 'same set of <nolink>methods</nolink>' is referring to multi-<nolink>method</nolink>
            <nolink>performances</nolink> (which are often, but not always, <nolink>spliced</nolink>). A <nolink>method</nolink> is always defined at the level of its <nolink>method title</nolink>. For example, Cambridge Surprise Minor and Cambridge Surprise Major are not the same <nolink>method</nolink> -- they are two different <nolink>methods</nolink> that are related (via a <nolink>method</nolink>
            <nolink>extension process</nolink>). Similarly Yorkshire Surprise Major and Yorkshire Delight Major are also two different <nolink>methods</nolink> -- ones that happen to share the same <nolink>method name</nolink>. We've amended 9.B.1 to clarify the above, and have also added that <nolink>variations</nolink> can also be used to generate a unique set of <nolink>methods</nolink> / <nolink>variations</nolink> with which to ring a <nolink>record length</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="14.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I am not sure if I would have classified a 'Little Path' in 4.A.6. As far as I know it refers only to <nolink>hunt bells</nolink>, but that section read on its own would suggest 2nds Place Bell Bristol is a Little Path. I would probably have just used the wording or similar in the relevant sections about Little Methods.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>A good point, and one that generated some debate among the framework team. We ended up thinking that a <nolink>little path</nolink> doesn't need to be confined to <nolink>hunt bells</nolink>, though we agree that's the most common usage. We've now added a paragraph to the further explanation of 4.A.6 clarifying this.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="15.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I note that nowhere is there a definition of 'Method Class' or 'Method Class Descriptor'. Sections 4 and 5 merely describe what they are. I wondered if these terms warranted an explanation somewhere.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Method Class is in fact defined -- see 4.A.1. We didn't think that Method Class Descriptor needed a separate, formal definition because the dictionary definition of Descriptor applies. We therefore went straight to defining how Method Class Descriptors are formed (5.B.1). As a general rule for the framework, we haven't defined terms where the normal dictionary definition of the word suffices.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="16.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I find it odd that 6.B.1(e) requires that the performance Report includes whether the <nolink>performance</nolink> was rung on towerbells or handbells. This fact is not included in the report and the explanatory notes suggest that this is indicated by the way in which items are submitted to Bellboard (other means of submitting <nolink>performance reports</nolink> are available). I know this is a linguistic point, but the report does not include this fact.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We were thinking here of handbell <nolink>performances</nolink> where each ringer only rings one bell. While these are rung infrequently, we wanted the framework to be able to accurately describe them if they are rung. BellBoard today has one form for one-bell-per-ringer, and another form for two-bells-per-ringer. A one-bell-per-ringer handbell <nolink>performance</nolink> could therefore look like a tower bell <nolink>performance</nolink>, so 6.B.1 e) gives a requirement to footnote that such a <nolink>performance</nolink> was on handbells. We've now edited 6.B.1 to include this point. The same issue might apply to a tower bell <nolink>performance</nolink> where each ringer rang two bells. But this would likely be posted on BellBoard with the name of each ringer entered twice against two bells, so the report would be clear as to what was rung.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="17.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I was surprised that the definition of <nolink>spliced</nolink> was reserved to the <nolink>performance</nolink> section; surely a <nolink>composition</nolink> can be described as <nolink>spliced</nolink> as well as the <nolink>performance</nolink>. It seems to appear too late in the framework in my opinion.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Yes we agree, and a good point. We've now defined <nolink>spliced</nolink> as part of 3.G (Compositions), and then stated that a <nolink>performance title</nolink> includes '<nolink>spliced</nolink>' if the <nolink>performance</nolink> included ringing a <nolink>spliced</nolink>
            <nolink>composition</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="18.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I am not sure I agree with the reporting standards and the examples given. Most QPs of <nolink>spliced</nolink>/mixed include the number of <nolink>methods</nolink> in the report, thereby taking, in the new definition, the <nolink>performance title</nolink> and part of the <nolink>performance detail</nolink>. I further note in <nolink>peal</nolink> databases (e.g. <nolink>peals</nolink>.co.uk) they are listed e.g. Spliced S Major (14). Would it not be better to require the number of <nolink>methods</nolink> to be part of the <nolink>performance title</nolink> where more than one <nolink>method</nolink> is rung?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Yes agreed -- multi-<nolink>method</nolink>
            <nolink>performances</nolink> posted on BellBoard often include the number of <nolink>methods</nolink> in the <nolink>performance title</nolink>. We've now updated 6.A to cover this, but made it optional as to where the number of <nolink>methods</nolink> is put, noting that The Ringing World still includes this in the <nolink>performance detail</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="19.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Section 9.2 refers to Variable Cover records; I can find no definition of what <nolink>variable cover</nolink> means in the framework, although references are made in various parts of the explanatory material, but do not use this term, apart from in the reporting examples.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Agreed. We've now added a definition of <nolink>variable cover</nolink> as part of 3.H (Cover Bells). Like <nolink>spliced</nolink>, <nolink>variable cover</nolink> is an attribute of a <nolink>composition</nolink>, so we've also now stated that a <nolink>performance title</nolink> includes '<nolink>variable cover</nolink>' if the <nolink>performance</nolink> included ringing a <nolink>variable cover</nolink>
            <nolink>composition</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="20.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Although the meaning is clear at all times in your text, I feel that there is a potential for misunderstanding in the use of the word '<nolink>extent</nolink>'. It is commonly used to mean (eg on 5) 'all 120 possible <nolink>changes</nolink> rung consecutively'. Thus '<nolink>call</nolink> two <nolink>extents</nolink> of Grandsire Doubles' would widely be interpreted to mean calling a 120 then another 120 immediately following, while a 240 that has each <nolink>row</nolink> once at hand and once at back would more often be called a 'double-<nolink>extent</nolink>'. But in your usage this 240 could be called 'two <nolink>extents</nolink>' as each <nolink>change</nolink> occurs twice, but the two <nolink>extents</nolink> are intertwined. You seem to anticipate this possible confusion by adding the clarifying remark 'The location of individual Rows within a Block of Rows does not have any bearing on <nolink>truth</nolink>.' Good - but I feel there is still a need to point out these two different possible interpretations of the word '<nolink>extent</nolink>' - or maybe have two different words??? Not sure what the solution is.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We agree ringing hasn't evolved clear terminology to differentiate between a <nolink>round block</nolink> comprising two <nolink>extents</nolink> (where the <nolink>rows</nolink> can appear in any order), and two individual <nolink>extents</nolink> rung consecutively. Where terminology like this hasn't evolved, it usually means that either the distinction often isn't important, or the distinction can be made using ordinary dictionary words (such as 'two individual <nolink>extents</nolink> rung consecutively' as above.) We've now updated 3.J.1 to point out the possibly ambiguity, and noted that care should be taken with communication where this distinction is important.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="21.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">The <nolink>blocks</nolink> were introduced early, but the counting of <nolink>rows</nolink> / <nolink>changes</nolink> gets a bit confusing especially without <nolink>round blocks</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Yes, <nolink>blocks</nolink> are introduced early (3.D) but this is deliberate. We tried many different ways of organising the information to minimise the number of forward references needed, and give the most intuitive groupings of terms, and we found that introducing <nolink>blocks</nolink> before <nolink>methods</nolink>, <nolink>calls</nolink>, <nolink>compositions</nolink> and <nolink>cover bells</nolink> gave the best results.</para>
          <para>The count of <nolink>changes</nolink> is the same regardless of whether the <nolink>block</nolink> is round or not. But when determining <nolink>truth</nolink> (which is a function of <nolink>rows</nolink>), the final <nolink>row</nolink> of a non-<nolink>round block</nolink> is included in the test, whereas for a <nolink>round block</nolink> it's excluded.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="22.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Truth also appears in 2.B.6 then with <nolink>accepted truth</nolink>. Truth to me really means no <nolink>row</nolink> repeated. Complete means every possible <nolink>row</nolink> at least once. We then later allow repeats to get <nolink>touches</nolink> longer than the <nolink>extent</nolink>, and adjust <nolink>truth</nolink> accordingly.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We're now reordered the framework so that the references to <nolink>truth</nolink> and <nolink>accepted truth</nolink> that were in 2.B.6 are now in Appendix E (Framework Development). This gives a better ordering of the information.</para>
          <para>There can be many different ways to apply <nolink>truth</nolink> (e.g. in a 240 of Doubles, each <nolink>row</nolink> appearing once at handstroke and once at backstroke might be considered 'more <nolink>true</nolink>' than a 240 where each <nolink>row</nolink> simply appears twice). In the interests of simplicity, we felt it would be valuable to have a single definition of <nolink>truth</nolink> that applies to all <nolink>stages</nolink> and all <nolink>lengths</nolink>, hence the definition used in 3.J.4. While 'complete' is a reasonably-well-known term for describing a <nolink>block</nolink> that contains each possible <nolink>row</nolink> at least once, we found we didn't need 'complete' to define any other term or requirement in the framework, so in the interests of simplicity, we didn't include 'complete' as a defined term.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="23.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.D.1. 'Block: A sequence of Changes, all with the same Stage, and the Rows produced by applying these Changes, starting from an initial Row.' So it is both the <nolink>changes</nolink> and the <nolink>rows</nolink>?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Yes, both the <nolink>changes</nolink> and the <nolink>rows</nolink>. A <nolink>block</nolink> results from applying a given sequence of <nolink>changes</nolink> to an initial <nolink>row</nolink>. While in practice, most ringing uses <nolink>rounds</nolink> as the initial <nolink>row</nolink>, a different <nolink>block</nolink> could be obtained from the same sequence of <nolink>changes</nolink> by using a different initial <nolink>row</nolink>. The two <nolink>blocks</nolink>' <nolink>changes</nolink> would be the same, but their <nolink>rows</nolink> would be different.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="24.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I do not understand the intention of 5.D.5.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>5.D.5 says 'Variations are incorporated into Compositions, including Spliced and Variable Cover Compositions, in the same way as Methods.'</para>
          <para>3.G.1 defines <nolink>composition</nolink> in terms of <nolink>method</nolink>(s). To be fully precise, we ought to define <nolink>composition</nolink> in terms of both <nolink>methods</nolink> and <nolink>variations</nolink>. But because it would be cumbersome to use '<nolink>methods</nolink> / <nolink>variations</nolink>' or similar in multiple <nolink>places</nolink> in the framework, we just used '<nolink>methods</nolink>', and 5.D.5 then serves to expand the other references to also include <nolink>variations</nolink>.</para>
          <para>Note that a <nolink>variation</nolink> isn't a <nolink>composition</nolink> -- it's the use of a <nolink>method</nolink> with certain, defined <nolink>call</nolink>(s). You still need a <nolink>composition</nolink> to specify how to use this <nolink>method</nolink> and its defined <nolink>call</nolink>(s).</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="25.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">2.C.2: What is <nolink>length</nolink> - is it <nolink>changes</nolink> or different <nolink>rows</nolink>? Currently <nolink>changes</nolink> as we start and end in <nolink>rounds</nolink>. But if <nolink>rows</nolink> - would ringing 5000 <nolink>rows</nolink> of major from pull-off and not finishing in <nolink>rounds</nolink> be a <nolink>peal</nolink>
              <nolink>length</nolink>? Probably not as defined as <nolink>changes</nolink> later.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>(Note that the former section 2 has now been moved to become part of Appendix E.)</para>
          <para>Yes, 5000 <nolink>rows</nolink> rung in total (from pull-off to stand) could only ever be a maximum of 4999 <nolink>changes</nolink> (and less if there are opening or closing <nolink>rounds</nolink>), so not a <nolink>peal</nolink>
            <nolink>length</nolink>. Length is always the number of <nolink>changes</nolink>, not the number of <nolink>rows</nolink> (see 3.I.2), and the number of <nolink>changes</nolink> is not affected by whether or not the <nolink>rows</nolink> are a <nolink>round block</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="26.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.A.1. Mention exclude 'nonuples' even though it is in some dictionaries.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We retained Octuples (<nolink>stage</nolink> 17) primarily because a <nolink>peal</nolink> of Octuples has been rung (this is the highest odd-<nolink>stage</nolink>
            <nolink>peal</nolink> rung to date). We didn't think nonuples was in the ringers' lexicon to the <nolink>extent</nolink> its absence needed to be explained, especially since even <nolink>stages</nolink> switch to English numbering starting at <nolink>stage</nolink> 14.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="27.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">'3.B.1 A sequence of numbered bells in which no bell appears more than once.' I don't like that as it allows bells to be omitted. Something like this would be better: A sequence of numbered bells in which each bell appears exactly once.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>The problem with the suggested definition is that 'each bell' is undefined. E.g. does it mean 'each bell in the tower' or even (to make a point) 'each bell in England'? The defining feature of a <nolink>row</nolink> is that no bell appears more than once, regardless of which bells do appear. When <nolink>rows</nolink> are combined into <nolink>blocks</nolink>, there is then an additional constraint that every <nolink>row</nolink> in the <nolink>block</nolink> comprises the same set of bells. This follows from the definition of <nolink>change</nolink> as a transposition. We've now added to the further explanations of 3.C.1 and 3.D.1 to clarify this point.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="28.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.C.1 I don't like <nolink>Change</nolink> for identity and <nolink>jump changes</nolink> - as that breaks the historic meaning, but using 'permutation' or 'generalised <nolink>change</nolink>' would make other definitions look messy.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> Need to make clear that <nolink>change</nolink> is the general transform, not the actual <nolink>row</nolink> to other <nolink>row</nolink> themselves. Perhaps needs an example:</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> 123456</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> 214365</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> is the same as</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> 346125</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> 431652</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Agreed on looking messy. In practice, we don't expect identity and <nolink>jump changes</nolink> to be rung frequently, so in normal usage '<nolink>adjacent change</nolink>' will be abbreviated to just '<nolink>change</nolink>' and the meaning will be clear from the context.</para>
          <para>On the second point, the explanation for 3.C.1 includes an example that shows that a <nolink>change</nolink> is a general transform that can be applied to any <nolink>row</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="29.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.F.1 Can you have dynamic <nolink>calls</nolink>? E.g. is the <nolink>call</nolink> of '<nolink>rounds</nolink>', a possibly <nolink>jump change</nolink>
              <nolink>call</nolink>, a dynamic <nolink>call</nolink>?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We haven't included dynamic <nolink>calls</nolink> as a separate type of <nolink>call</nolink> as their use seems unlikely. They could be added to a future version of the framework if <nolink>compositions</nolink> emerge that use them, and if having a central definition of dynamic <nolink>calls</nolink> is thought to aid ringers in communicating about <nolink>method</nolink> ringing.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="30.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Is a <nolink>call</nolink> part of a <nolink>method</nolink>? E.g. ringing 14 instead of 12 in Cambridge surprise Major doesn't affect the number of <nolink>changes</nolink> of Cambridge. What about ringing 18 - is that one <nolink>change</nolink> of Primrose Surprise, or Original, or Bristol Surprise?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Calls are separate from <nolink>methods</nolink>, in the sense that a given <nolink>call</nolink> can be used with many different <nolink>methods</nolink>, and many different <nolink>calls</nolink> can be used with a single <nolink>method</nolink>. However, when reporting the number of <nolink>changes</nolink> rung of a given <nolink>method</nolink> in a <nolink>performance</nolink>, the count includes those <nolink>changes</nolink> that were modifications to the <nolink>method</nolink>'s <nolink>changes</nolink> resulting from <nolink>calls</nolink>. The explanation for 3.F.1 provides more detail.</para>
          <para>Ringing a 18 <nolink>change</nolink> as the <nolink>leadend change</nolink> in Cambridge S Major is an example of the well-known problem of overlap in describing <nolink>method</nolink> ringing. The same set of <nolink>changes</nolink> can be described in many different ways, and there's no satisfactory way of eliminating this overlap. Ringers therefore use their judgement in deciding which is the most appropriate way to describe a given set of <nolink>changes</nolink>. A 18 <nolink>leadend change</nolink> in Cambridge could be described as a <nolink>composition</nolink> of <nolink>spliced</nolink> Cambridge and Primrose, or the 18 <nolink>change</nolink> could be described as an additional <nolink>call</nolink> in a Cambridge <nolink>composition</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="31.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.I.2 With whole pull Plain Bob Minor (<nolink>identity change</nolink>), do you count the <nolink>identity changes</nolink>?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>An <nolink>extent</nolink> of Plain Bob Minor with each <nolink>row</nolink> rung at handstroke and backstroke before moving to the next <nolink>row</nolink> could be reported as 1440 Plain Bob Minor, thereby counting the <nolink>identity changes</nolink>. This would be a <nolink>true</nolink>
            <nolink>performance</nolink>. Alternatively, the <nolink>performance</nolink> could be reported as 720 Plain Bob Minor with a disclosure added, per 6.C.2 n), explaining the whole pull ringing. Either approach would be valid and it is left to ringers to use their best judgement in deciding how to report. Note that reporting 1440 <nolink>changes</nolink> would give a more expected alignment with the reported time of the <nolink>performance</nolink>. Also note that at higher <nolink>stages</nolink>, whole pull ringing would almost certainly be false, leading to a disclosure under 6.C.2 b).</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="32.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">"Technical comments: As discussed above under Compositions (Section 3.G), it is possible for a Composition to use two or more Methods side by side, or to use two or more Compositions side by side. As a further <nolink>variation</nolink>, a Composition might also result in an interior Cover Bell. For example, a Composition might be designed to be used with Maximus Rows, using a Doubles Method in Places 1 to 5 and a Minor Method in Places 7 to 12. 6th's Place does not have any Methods operating on it, and therefore 6th's Place contains a Cover Bell. In this case, the Composition would produce Maximus Changes (and therefore have a Stage of Maximus), and each of its Changes would include the place notation '6'."</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> I read that as being an Effective Stage of Cinques.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> I guess with fixed bells in the middle you could use <nolink>jump changes</nolink> to swap bells from the front to the back.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Yes to both. The <nolink>effective stage</nolink> is Cinques (even though the <nolink>composition</nolink> has a <nolink>stage</nolink> of Maximus), and <nolink>jump changes</nolink> could be used to jump between, say, 5th's <nolink>place</nolink> and 7th's <nolink>place</nolink>, thereby leaving 6th's <nolink>place</nolink> as an interior <nolink>cover bell</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="33.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I have never met any ringer who thought a <nolink>change</nolink> was anything other than an order of all the bells being rung. You do not need a name for the transition from one to another.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> I have never heard the term <nolink>stage</nolink> before, I assume this refers to doubles major etc., why not just write number of changing bells or NCB if that is too long.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> You do not define lead especially when it is used in reference to <nolink>principles</nolink>. To me <nolink>principles</nolink> do not have leads.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>On your first point, '<nolink>row</nolink>' and '<nolink>change</nolink>' have indeed been used interchangeably over the years to refer to what the framework describes as a '<nolink>row</nolink>'. In the earliest ringing publications the term '<nolink>change</nolink>' was used to cover both the process of moving the bells and the resulting sequence. However, by the late 1800s, technical writers needed to split the process from the result, and these terms became '<nolink>row</nolink>' and '<nolink>change</nolink>'. E.g. from 'A Note on Grandsire Triples', W.H. Thompson, Macmillan and Bowes, 1886, page 7: 'Any one permutation of the 7 bells is called a '<nolink>row</nolink>'. The Decisions have been making the distinction between a <nolink>row</nolink> and <nolink>change</nolink> since at least 1970.</para>
          <para>As with many terms, this distinction has not been made consistently, either in common parlance or ringing literature. To address this, we've added the following to Section 3.B.1:</para>
          <para>'Note that what is defined as a Row in this section is sometimes described as a Change in common ringing parlance, and this usage of Change will be found in some <nolink>method</nolink> ringing books and articles. The framework separately uses Change as the transition between two Rows (see Section 3.C) and this distinction between Row and Change is important in defining a number of other <nolink>method</nolink> ringing terms used in the framework. Row is the preferred term wherever possible.'</para>
          <para>We do need a term for the transition between <nolink>rows</nolink> because these are the building <nolink>blocks</nolink> for <nolink>methods</nolink> and <nolink>compositions</nolink>. E.g. Plain Bob Minor comprises the <nolink>changes</nolink> x16x16x16x16x16x12 -- here it's clear that <nolink>changes</nolink> are referring to transitions, and not to an order of bells. In a <nolink>composition</nolink>, a bob might replace a 12 <nolink>change</nolink> with a 14 <nolink>change</nolink>, and so on.</para>
          <para>On your second point, <nolink>stage</nolink> does refer to Doubles, Major, etc. It's an established term -- e.g. used in the Decisions since at least 1970.</para>
          <para>Finally, <nolink>principles</nolink> do have leads in the same way as any other <nolink>method</nolink>. We often don't think of them this way, probably because the most well-known <nolink>principle</nolink> (Stedman) lends itself to being thought of in sixes, where we don't even normally start and finish at a six-end. But the same lead structure is there (Stedman has 12 <nolink>changes</nolink> in a lead), and if you look at other <nolink>principles</nolink> (e.g. Double Éire Minor) the lead structure is more apparent.</para>
          <para>Not considering <nolink>principles</nolink> to have leads is also partly historic. Principles used not to be considered <nolink>methods</nolink>, and were said to be made up of divisions rather than leads. But the Decisions have considered <nolink>principles</nolink> to be <nolink>methods</nolink> since at least 1970. Between 1970 and 1999 the Decisions referred to <nolink>principles</nolink> being made up of divisions or leads. In 1999, division was dropped. Consequently the framework drafting team have seen no reason to retain the term division when lead is sufficient, and using one term for all <nolink>methods</nolink> is simpler.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="permissiveness">
    <title>C. Permissiveness</title>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem mrf:label="1.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I would query whether it is necessary to restrict Doubles <nolink>variations</nolink> to those capable of producing a single <nolink>extent</nolink>
              <nolink>round block</nolink> (5.D.4). If <nolink>methods</nolink> false in the <nolink>plain course</nolink> are permitted, why can't a <nolink>variation</nolink> that cannot produce a <nolink>true</nolink> 120? Considering the rest of the framework, this seems somewhat prescriptive. There are Doubles <nolink>variations</nolink> that have been rung and named already for which a 120 is not possible, but a 240 can be rung (e.g. Heterodox Doubles: Plain Bob with a New Bob bob).</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Yes, good point -- we agree this goes against our descriptive / permissive mandate (it was copied over from the current Decisions with insufficient scrutiny). We have now removed this requirement.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="2.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I think that it is slightly odd that <nolink>jump changes</nolink> are added, but are then also added to the list of items to be mentioned in <nolink>performance reports</nolink> as not conforming to the norms.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>In line with our descriptive / permissive mandate, we've included <nolink>jump changes</nolink> in the framework so that if they're rung, there is terminology to describe them. But since <nolink>jump changes</nolink> have not been the norm in <nolink>method</nolink> ringing, we want their use to be clear in <nolink>performance reports</nolink>. Since <nolink>methods</nolink> that include <nolink>jump changes</nolink> will have 'Jump' in their <nolink>method titles</nolink>, additional disclosure is therefore only needed when (a) jump <nolink>calls</nolink> are used with non-<nolink>jump methods</nolink>, and (b) <nolink>variations</nolink> with <nolink>jump changes</nolink> are used (<nolink>variations</nolink> don't use <nolink>class descriptors</nolink> in their titles). This is outlined in the further explanation of Section 6.C.2.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="3.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I would urge the proponents of these <nolink>changes</nolink> to tread very carefully indeed. History shows that when traditional and ingrained systems are swept away, those who are not prepared to put up with it will break away from the existing structures and form their own traditional groups. Anglicanism is a good example where there are now thousands of traditionalists broken away from Lambeth throughout the world. An alternative Council of Traditional English Change Ringers would be a disaster for the art given the challenges to ringing posed by on-going collapse of the Church of England.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>The Decisions have been a source of controversy since the formation of the Council, and many believe the Decisions' approach of ruling out ringing that hasn't been done before has harmed the Council's reputation, especially among more advanced ringers. The motion to switch to a descriptive / permissive approach passed with a very clear majority at the Edinburgh CC meeting.</para>
          <para>However we recognise that traditionalists won't like all the forms of <nolink>method</nolink> ringing that the framework describes. The framework uses a disclosure approach so that <nolink>performances</nolink> that differ from <nolink>method</nolink> ringing norms can be identified as such.</para>
          <para>There is also, deliberately, nothing in the framework that prevents a group of traditionalist ringers from forming a society (which could become affiliated with the Central Council) that implements additional restrictions on what it considers <nolink>methods</nolink> or <nolink>peals</nolink>. For example, this society might choose only to recognise <nolink>peals</nolink> of Triples and below that are rung in whole <nolink>extents</nolink>, and only that involve <nolink>methods</nolink> that are <nolink>principles</nolink> or are <nolink>hunters</nolink> with Plain Bob or Grandsire <nolink>leadheads</nolink> / <nolink>leadends</nolink>.</para>
          <para>Ultimately ringers with a wide range of opinions have to find ways to coexist with one another, and we believe that a descriptive / permissive approach, paired with disclosure and the ability of like-minded ringers to group together to focus on the types of ringing they're interested in, is the most likely way to achieve this.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="4.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I think that what we should strive to avoid is offending against first <nolink>principles</nolink> of <nolink>change</nolink> ringing that have been established for centuries. Thus I cannot support the introduction of <nolink>jump changes</nolink> and multiple covering bells in <nolink>peals</nolink>. The <nolink>peal</nolink> is a benchmark of achievement and there is no case for allowing people who can barely handle a bell in Rounds to follow another bell for three hours in the pretense that they are now a <nolink>peal</nolink> ringer. Extra covering bells have a <nolink>place</nolink> in Quarters to give rope-time to learners, but not in <nolink>peal</nolink> ringing. If this is permitted we will soon see a <nolink>peal</nolink> of Minimus rung on 12 with 8 covering bells which would bring our art into disrepute.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">It appears from what has been published that a recordable <nolink>peal</nolink> could now be rung on 1 and 2 bells. That is a nonsense. However what I do want to see, and have advocated for many years is the acceptance of Singles. I do not see a case for saying that a <nolink>band</nolink> who have worked away at a probably rough 3 for nearly three hours have not rung a Peal. Singles should be the basic minimum <nolink>stage</nolink> for <nolink>change</nolink> ringing.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I am much concerned that ringing is going to join the Gadarene rush to abolish all standards so as to be 'more inclusive'. The abolition of traditional standards is a disease. Ringing should work towards improving standards, not abolishing them to placate the PC brigade.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Much Central Council time was taken up debating whether 4-bell <nolink>peals</nolink> should be recognised. We could clearly spend more time debating whether 3-bell <nolink>peals</nolink> should be recognised, and then 2-bell <nolink>peals</nolink>. Similarly, we could spend much time in the future debating whether <nolink>jump changes</nolink> and multiple <nolink>cover bells</nolink> should be recognised. With the CRAG mandate, the Council has decided this is not a good approach. The mandate was very clear -- the aim of the framework is to be permissive and describe what ringers choose to ring, rather than specifying rules over what the Council will and will not recognise. This is a direct response by the Council to the recognition that the previous system hasn't worked well, has caused much controversy, and has harmed the Council's reputation, obscuring much of its other good work. It's now time to try something new -- namely to provide standard terminology for ringers to describe what they rang, and leave it to them to decide what they want to ring.</para>
          <para>The aim of trying to use the framework to enforce ringing standards (i.e. quality) is also misguided in our view. Standards vary widely by <nolink>band</nolink> and location, and a one-size-fits-all central approach will inevitably result in the bar being set too high for some and too low for others. Encouraging improved ringing quality is better addressed at the local level, with the Central Council possibly providing guidance / tips, and/or promoting training events and similar.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="5.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Method ringing should alter the order of the bells at every <nolink>row</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>This is the question of whether the <nolink>identity change</nolink> should be recognised. For example, an <nolink>extent</nolink> of Plain Bob Doubles can be turned into a <nolink>true</nolink> 240 by calling a single with place notation 12345 at two points 120 <nolink>changes</nolink> apart. This 240 has the nice feature of every <nolink>row</nolink> appearing once at handstroke and once at backstroke.</para>
          <para>Since a 12345 <nolink>change</nolink> results in every bell staying in the same <nolink>place</nolink> from one <nolink>row</nolink> to the next, it is the <nolink>identity change</nolink> for Doubles. Given there are valid uses of <nolink>identity changes</nolink>, as shown in the example above, and that our mandate is to be permissive and descriptive, we believe <nolink>identity changes</nolink> should be covered in the framework. It is then up to individual ringers and <nolink>bands</nolink> to decide whether they want to make use of them.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="6.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">'Simple and permissive descriptive framework for ringing with only the minimal detail required to maintain the historical record.' I don't think this is achievable or particularly desirable goal as simplification and permissiveness actually leads to more complication explaining ordinary ringing.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>This is the mandate we were given, which was decided by a very clear majority vote of the Central Council, and the framework team believes it was the right mandate. However, it's certainly correct that increasing permissiveness does also increase complexity, and there's a limit to how simple you can make a <nolink>method</nolink> ringing framework (we've interpreted the mandate as being to make the framework <emphasis role="italic">as simple as possible</emphasis>).</para>
          <para>The framework aims to cover all types of <nolink>method</nolink> ringing so it isn't designed as a primer for new ringers, though we've tried to make it accessible to as many ringers as possible. Ringing authors might develop or update guides (e.g. for new / developing ringers) that just cover the parts of the framework that relate to what is more commonly rung.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="7.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.H.1 Does this allow continuously leading bells? In major could you have a <nolink>method</nolink> with a fixed bell leading, but considered as part of the <nolink>method</nolink>?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Yes to both. The former is described in the further explanation of 3.H.1. The latter is an example of the well-known problem of overlap in describing <nolink>method</nolink> ringing. You could describe a continuously leading bell in 8-bell <nolink>rows</nolink> as a leading <nolink>cover bell</nolink> rung with a Triples <nolink>method</nolink>, or as a Major <nolink>method</nolink> with a <nolink>stationary bell</nolink> in 1st's <nolink>place</nolink>. A leading <nolink>cover bell</nolink> with a Triples <nolink>method</nolink> might be the simpler description of what was rung, but if there was also a <nolink>stationary bell</nolink> in, say, 5th's <nolink>place</nolink>, and both <nolink>stationary bells</nolink> were affected by <nolink>calls</nolink>, thereby changing the <nolink>stationary bells</nolink>, the <nolink>changes</nolink> might be better described as a <nolink>composition</nolink> of a Major <nolink>method</nolink>. Ringers therefore use their judgement to decide how best to describe a given set of <nolink>changes</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Perhaps the online version of The Ringing World could <nolink>change</nolink> reports to match the reader's wishes. E.g. if you don't agree with <nolink>jump changes</nolink>, you could filter out any <nolink>performances</nolink> that used them.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>The purpose of 6.C (<nolink>performance norms</nolink>) is to make ringers aware when <nolink>performances</nolink> include features that differ from common practice. It will, of <nolink>course</nolink>, be for The Ringing World to decide if and how to make use of this information, but it could indeed potentially be used to let readers filter out certain types of <nolink>performances</nolink> that they're not interested in reading about.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">It's also a bit silly to ring partial <nolink>extents</nolink> of minor, doubles, etc even if you do want a funny number in the <nolink>peal</nolink> report. I wouldn't stop someone from doing it, but I don't want to see it reported as a <nolink>peal</nolink>, or on a <nolink>peal</nolink> board.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>The <nolink>change</nolink> to recognise partial <nolink>extents</nolink> was made in 2016, passing with a large Central Council majority, so this isn't something new in the framework. To not recognise partial <nolink>extents</nolink> goes against the permissive and descriptive elements of the framework mandate, which was also passed by a large Central Council majority.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="10.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">2.A.1 There is an assumption in this that all ringing can be defined in terms of <nolink>methods</nolink> and I believe this to be wrong. The term `<nolink>method</nolink>' should have a very specific meaning and what should be described is <nolink>change</nolink> ringing which is the general term for what we do. Proposal H did not mention <nolink>methods</nolink>. Throughout the framework there is undue mention of <nolink>methods</nolink> where it should be <nolink>change</nolink> ringing.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> The definition of a <nolink>method</nolink> seems to be virtually identical to a <nolink>block</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> The definitions used are not ones which would be understandable or recognisable to an ordinary ringer. There seems far too much emphasis on mathematical concepts rather than practical ringing. For instance `the <nolink>identity change</nolink>' is not a <nolink>change</nolink> in the terminology of ringing it is simply a repeated <nolink>row</nolink>. I'm afraid this framework does not do what the Council asked for and needs a fundamental reevaluation; the present team and reviewers have too many people from a computing and mathematical background and seem out of <nolink>touch</nolink> with practical ringing in the wider world.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Many ringers would agree with the idea that a <nolink>method</nolink> should have a more limited meaning than just any sequence of <nolink>changes</nolink>. The problem is that this falls into the category of "sounds good, doesn't work". In over 100 years of trying, the ringing community hasn't found a limited definition of '<nolink>method</nolink>' that is widely agreed upon. Some of the harshest battles in 20th century ringing related to the definition of a <nolink>method</nolink>. E.g. see the book 'Forbidden Methods' by Karl Grave (2010, published by The Whiting Society of Ringers) where some <nolink>methods</nolink> were described as 'illegitimate' or even 'bastards'. And see <link xlink:href="https://bb.ringingworld.co.uk/view.php?id=1100503">here</link> for a more recent dispute over the definition of a <nolink>method</nolink>.</para>
          <para>Progress comes from learning from the past. Since there is no practicable way of limiting the definition of a <nolink>method</nolink> without also ruling out sensible cases, the only solution is to enable any sequence of <nolink>changes</nolink> to be named as a <nolink>method</nolink>. This is what the framework does, and it's also consistent with our permissive / descriptive mandate. We trust that ringers will be sensible in what they choose to name as <nolink>methods</nolink>. And if they're not sensible, Section 5.E.3 of the framework contains an anti-abuse provision.</para>
          <para>On Method vs Block, we've now added additional explanation to 3.E.1 on the difference between these two terms. The distinction is key -- a <nolink>method</nolink> is the process (i.e. the <nolink>changes</nolink>) and a <nolink>block</nolink> is the result of applying the process (i.e. the <nolink>changes</nolink> plus the <nolink>rows</nolink> produced, given a specified starting <nolink>row</nolink>).</para>
          <para>We recognise the problem of self-selection in a project like this. The sort of people who are interested in becoming politicians are often the last people you want running a country, and the same may be <nolink>true</nolink> of people who volunteer to develop a <nolink>method</nolink> ringing framework. The only responses we can give are:</para>
          <orderedlist numeration="arabic" role="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>We've been very conscious of the need to keep things as simple as possible. Many solutions that were more elegant or more purist were ruled out of the framework because we decided they were too complex to include.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The framework isn’t intended as a primer on <nolink>method</nolink> ringing for people new to the Exercise – there are other publications that capably meet that need. The intended audience for the framework starts at the level of ringers who are already familiar with the basics of <nolink>method</nolink> ringing.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>To be effective, the framework needs to be able to describe all reasonably foreseeable forms of <nolink>method</nolink> ringing, not just 'everyday' ringing. Otherwise it's not a framework -- it's a limited description of some common forms of <nolink>method</nolink> ringing. We don't believe that's what the Central Council intended. We don't dispute that covering all foreseeable forms of <nolink>method</nolink> ringing means there is some complexity to the framework. But we think we've simplified things about as much as is possible, and we deliberately included lots of examples, diagrams and explanations to try and make things as clear as possible.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
          <para>At the same time, we're open to any suggestions on how the framework could be simplified. There will be subsequent versions of the framework, which will give the opportunity for new ideas to be considered.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="11.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I’m not terribly knowledgeable technically, so I have just one comment. I understand that the proposed framework would permit <nolink>jump changes</nolink>. If that is so, then I disagree with it for two chief reasons. First, agree with it or not, one of the things that has always distinguished <nolink>change</nolink> ringing is its incrementalism. Change ringing patterns have been defined by very few rules, but one of them is that a bell can move only one <nolink>place</nolink> in the <nolink>row</nolink>. This means that <nolink>change</nolink> ringing is a restrictive musical form—but what of that? It simply means that we find enjoyment in working within a narrow musical field—one that shows that great <nolink>changes</nolink> can be accomplished incrementally, over time. An analogy in poetry would be to the sonnet. The sonnet is extremely well defined and has been that way for centuries. Why <nolink>change</nolink> it? Or at least, if you write a poem in a different structure, why not concede that the result may be a very good poem, but it is not a sonnet? And really, does that matter so much—unless perchance we are counting sonnets that we have recited? Second, I think that moving only one <nolink>place</nolink> in a <nolink>row</nolink> is a safety consideration. If you encourage <nolink>methods</nolink> that include <nolink>jump changes</nolink>, then there will be more stays lost, more limbs broken, and more embarrassing press coverage of ringers being lowered out of towers by stretcher, crane, or helicopter. The Church and its insurers will start asking questions. All this should be avoided. For these reasons I would respectfully suggest that if leading theoreticians want to ring <nolink>jump changes</nolink>, then those <nolink>methods</nolink> and <nolink>compositions</nolink> should simply be among the things that are deemed noncompliant. Nothing prevents people from trying to accomplish them, from celebrating those accomplishments, or from counting them as <nolink>peals</nolink> in their personal totals. But <nolink>jump changes</nolink> lack official CCCBR imprimatur and so the Exercise can say that they are not typical of what we do. Let’s not break something, only then to find out the very good reasons why it has held its current form for centuries.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We agree that incrementalism and working within a restricted space is a key attraction of <nolink>method</nolink> ringing. The difficulty, and where your analogy breaks down, is that if someone writes a poem that is not a sonnet, it is still a poem. If we say <nolink>jump changes</nolink> are not <nolink>method</nolink> ringing, what are they? We don't have a term. And even if we invented a new term, many would object because they consider <nolink>jump changes</nolink> to be part of <nolink>method</nolink> ringing, and we would be trying to tell them otherwise.</para>
          <para>That's why we introduced the term '<nolink>adjacent change</nolink>' -- to provide a subset term (like sonnet) that enables ringers to describe a piece of ringing that only used traditional <nolink>changes</nolink>, should they wish to emphasise this.</para>
          <para>We think your safety concerns on <nolink>jump changes</nolink> are a little overstated. If you ring at a 4-bell tower, you have to move your bell further for an <nolink>adjacent change</nolink> than you do for a 2-<nolink>place</nolink> jump when ringing on 10-bells. The risks of <nolink>jump changes</nolink> seem far lower than those involved when, say, teaching someone to ring, ringing bells down, or even walking down a narrow or steep tower spiral staircase.</para>
          <para>Furthermore, ringing safety is better addressed at the local level -- a one-size-fits-all restriction at the Central Council level isn't appropriate. Some towers have experienced ringers who will have no difficulty executing <nolink>jump changes</nolink>. Other towers have beginners who will need close supervision even when ringing <nolink>adjacent changes</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="12.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">On the subject of <nolink>jump changes</nolink>: The new framework has done an excellent job of allowing the flexibility for <nolink>bands</nolink> and composers to explore a multitude of constructs and so it would seem to me to be inconsistent for <nolink>jump changes</nolink> to be excluded simply because they have not been part of the traditional framework. I do agree that unfettered inclusion could <nolink>lead</nolink> to some bizarre results and so the challenge is to provide a <nolink>little</nolink> bit of structure and then see what happens. My proposal is to follow the principal that the primary objective is to allow people to describe accurately what they ring. To do this we should start by saying that <nolink>changes</nolink> are classified as jump-n. Normal <nolink>methods</nolink> are jump-1 (i.e. no bell <nolink>changes</nolink> more than one <nolink>place</nolink>) but obviously by <nolink>extension</nolink> we could define a jump-2 <nolink>method</nolink> and so on. It would also be helpful to define whether we have a <nolink>jump method</nolink> or are using jump <nolink>calls</nolink>. A standard <nolink>method</nolink> with jump bobs might be an interesting idea, not everyone's cup of tea but if it allowed better <nolink>compositions</nolink> in <nolink>methods</nolink> with a lot of falseness it might get some traction. I don't think the reservation that <nolink>bands</nolink> might claim a <nolink>performance</nolink> by claiming 'Go <nolink>rounds</nolink>' is of any concern. At the end of the day we rely on the honesty of <nolink>bands</nolink> and conductors to report what was done and not everyone has the same standards with the rules we've got so to say we are not allowing something because we can't trust people to use it responsibly is not the way to go!</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We agree with all your points. The purpose of the framework is to provide terminology to describe what ringers choose to ring, not to try and impose limits -- that was our permissive / descriptive mandate. Your jump-n notation is a good suggestion -- it would be interesting to see in a <nolink>performance report</nolink> involving <nolink>jump changes</nolink> what the size of the jumps were. We haven't included this notation in the first version of the framework given that <nolink>jump changes</nolink> are rarely rung, but we've tabled this for consideration in a future version of the framework.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="callchanges">
    <title>D. Call Changes</title>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem mrf:label="1.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Shouldn't the new framework also cover <nolink>call</nolink>
              <nolink>change</nolink> ringing?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Change ringing can be viewed as having two separate branches: <nolink>method</nolink> ringing and <nolink>call</nolink>
            <nolink>change</nolink> ringing. (The term '<nolink>call</nolink>
            <nolink>changes</nolink>' is probably a simplification of what originally may have been 'called <nolink>changes</nolink>'.) When looking at how the framework (and previously the Decisions) supports <nolink>method</nolink> ringing, one finds that <nolink>call</nolink>
            <nolink>change</nolink> ringing doesn't require the same support. There's no central library of <nolink>call</nolink>
            <nolink>change</nolink> callings, no tradition of publishing <nolink>call</nolink>
            <nolink>change</nolink>
            <nolink>performances</nolink>, or ringing <nolink>record lengths</nolink> of <nolink>call</nolink>
            <nolink>changes</nolink>, and no practice of classifying <nolink>call</nolink>
            <nolink>changes</nolink> or extending sets of <nolink>call</nolink>
            <nolink>changes</nolink> to give related sets at higher <nolink>stages</nolink>. While there's no reason why the above couldn't develop, it hasn't to date.</para>
          <para>For the reasons above, and also so we can keep our focus on implementing the framework for <nolink>method</nolink> ringing sooner rather than later, we therefore don't propose to include a description of <nolink>call</nolink>
            <nolink>change</nolink> ringing in the framework at this <nolink>stage</nolink>. However, there may be a case for adding this in a subsequent version of the framework if the ringing community thinks this would be useful. Alternatively, a separate framework for <nolink>call</nolink>
            <nolink>change</nolink> ringing could be developed. In either case, this should be led by specialists in the <nolink>call</nolink>
            <nolink>changes</nolink> field.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="methodnaming">
    <title>E. Method Naming</title>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem mrf:label="1.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I notice in the MicroSiril library that Baldrickdifferentiallittlebob is included in the Plain library. Where is it in the CCCBR library?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>In CompLib it can be found <link xlink:href="https://complib.org/method/search/?title=baldrick%20differential">here</link>. In the text files at <link xlink:href="https://methods.cccbr.org.uk">https://methods.cccbr.org.uk</link>, it appears in the Plain file. While there's a separate file for Differentials, this only includes <nolink>differentials</nolink> without <nolink>hunt bells</nolink>. Differential <nolink>hunters</nolink> are included with the corresponding classes of non-<nolink>differential</nolink>
            <nolink>hunters</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="2.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">5.E/F: Existing <nolink>methods</nolink> should retain their old names as well as there new names. It should be valid to publish <nolink>performances</nolink> using either name. New <nolink>methods</nolink> should not use old names.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We think it would be too confusing and complicated to have (a) <nolink>methods</nolink> reported using more than one name, and (b) the previous name of a <nolink>method</nolink> whose name has been changed (e.g. due to a classification <nolink>change</nolink> that resulted in a naming conflict) to be reserved against future use. We think a better approach is for the <nolink>methods library</nolink> to be able to record alternative names by which certain <nolink>methods</nolink> are known, and for these names to be searchable within the library.</para>
          <para>In any case, we only expect a very small number of <nolink>methods</nolink> to require a name <nolink>change</nolink> under the framework (see Appendix F.1). Some <nolink>methods</nolink> will get a new title (= name + class + <nolink>stage</nolink>) because of classification <nolink>changes</nolink>, but the vast majority of these will keep the same <nolink>method name</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="3.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Relating to <nolink>method titles</nolink> changing under a revised classification system, what happens, for example, if you rename Champion Surprise Major to Champion Major? Can someone then create a new Champion Surprise Major, or is that name now dead?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>As per the previous question, we don't propose to restrict re-use of a name where a <nolink>method</nolink> that previously used the name has been retitled. We do propose keeping a record of alternative / historical names used for <nolink>methods</nolink> in the <nolink>methods library</nolink> where appropriate.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="4.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">How are spaces in <nolink>method names</nolink> treated? Is 'London No 3' different from 'Londonno3'? I guess not, but can't see how the algorithm mentioned removes spaces.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Item 4 of Appendix B (Method Name Syntax) describes the process for determining whether two <nolink>method names</nolink> are considered the same. The aim of this process is to prevent <nolink>method names</nolink> being so similar that they could easily be confused. E.g. London No. 3 and London No 3 would be considered the same under this process. However, the process doesn't go as far as eliminating all spaces between other characters. Multiple spaces are reduced to a single space, but a single space is considered different from no space. London No 3 would therefore be considered different from Londonno3. There are already examples of this in the <nolink>method library</nolink> -- for example, Whitehall Surprise Major and White Hall Surprise Major have both been named, as have Christchurch Surprise Royal and Christ Church Surprise Royal. The Technical &amp; Taxonomy Workgroup will review similar <nolink>method names</nolink> when they occur, and may request that a <nolink>band</nolink> uses a different name to avoid possible confusion.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="5.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">What will happen to <nolink>methods</nolink> and <nolink>variations</nolink> that have already been named with name clashes, if they exist?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>The process for this is described in Appendix F.1 Transitional Arrangements, which also links to a schedule of the affected <nolink>methods</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="wholepullringing">
    <title>F. Whole-Pull Ringing</title>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem mrf:label="1.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">It would be useful to allow whole pull <nolink>performances</nolink> (i.e. every <nolink>row</nolink> repeated) -- but only when half-muffled.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>A very important aspect of the new framework is that we are not seeking to allow or disallow certain types of ringing. Instead we're aiming to provide standard terminology that enables ringers to describe what they rang, so that other ringers can read about ringing <nolink>performances</nolink> and be clear on what was rung.</para>
          <para>Whole pull ringing doesn't follow the norms of <nolink>method</nolink> ringing. Under Section 6.C n) the report of a whole pull <nolink>performance</nolink> should therefore include a disclosure that the <nolink>composition</nolink> was rung in whole pulls. As noted above, whole pull ringing can work well when the bells are half-muffled.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="implementation">
    <title>G. Implementation</title>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem mrf:label="1.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Link to <nolink>methods library</nolink> is missing; Section 5.A.1 (expanded)</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Thanks -- this has now been added.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="2.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">We should be prepared to get something agreed and continue to enhance &amp; improve explanations over time rather than seek perfection before we publish. What is there is already much better than what we have.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>The framework team agrees. The first version of the framework won't be perfect, and it's doubtful there could ever be a perfect framework. We envisage a process of continuous improvement to the framework over time as issues and inconsistencies are discovered, and as <nolink>method</nolink> ringing continues to evolve.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="3.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">This may be the first location where I found a reasonable description of <nolink>leadhead</nolink> codes! An even better explanation of what these are and why they are important is almost certainly outside the scope of this framework, however, a lack of good understanding of what these are and why they are important is one of many barriers for new composers/conductors, especially those who do not have access to an experienced conductor in a mentoring kind of way.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We think you're right that this is probably beyond the scope of the framework, at least for the first version. However we've now added 'They are a useful shorthand for communicating the Lead order of a Method' to the first paragraph of Appendix C, to give a high-level indication of their purpose.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="4.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">My own belief is that you should stop describing this work as 'technical' in the sense of difficult for ordinary people to understand. It is 'technical' in that it relates to a detailed understanding of what a <nolink>method</nolink> is. And for that, of <nolink>course</nolink>, it takes time to absorb in detail. However, if any of the framework requires additional (undocumented within the framework) knowledge in order to understand what the framework means, then this is a failure. I am not a composer, <nolink>method</nolink> designer, and not a very experienced conductor, but I am perfectly capable of understanding what these mean and their significance to the Exercise. And perhaps one day I might become one of these things, so making it accessible (which on the whole you have succeeded at) would help that to happen. You should also stop portraying this work as 'of interest to only a few ringers'. This is only partly <nolink>true</nolink>. Most ringers assume they are not interested because they are continually told it is not interesting. But every ringer understands that a <nolink>method name</nolink> consists of a title, a classification and a <nolink>stage</nolink>. This is part of the framework and is built into how we teach people about ringing. OK, the very finest detail is more esoteric, but then so are certain aspects of ringing history, or bellframe construction, or safeguarding issues, none of which we portray as too difficult for the ordinary ringer to understand.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We agree that the framework shouldn't require any additional (undocumented within the framework) knowledge in order to understand what the framework means, and this has been one of our key goals. We hope we've achieved this, but welcome any suggestions on an ongoing basis on how the framework might be made clearer.</para>
          <para>It hasn't been our intention to portray the framework as 'too difficult for the ordinary ringer to understand'. The framework is 'technical' in the sense that it includes theory and mechanics of <nolink>method</nolink> ringing, so the fine detail may be of more interest to specialists than to generalists, but the fundamental content underpins <nolink>method</nolink> ringing and should be accessible to any interested ringer.</para>
          <para>We have been cautious not to give the impression that we think every ringer ought to be spending lots of time studying the framework. Ringing has lots of problems to solve, including existential ones relating to the declining number of ringers and ageing demographics. We therefore wanted to get the balance right in saying there is value in having a well-thought-out framework for describing <nolink>method</nolink> ringing, but there are also many other challenges facing the Exercise that need ringers' time and energy.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="5.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Appendix E.D.3 (formerly 2.B.3): Also add excludes concords (= chords) (see Campanalogia) where two bells ring at the same time. Also we are not considering irregular spaced ringing. Handstroke gap or cartwheel distinction also not part of ringing framework. Also combination - consider ringing minor cartwheel, but with open handstroke when tenor is behind previously!</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Appendix E.D.3 already notes that chords are outside the boundaries of what is considered <nolink>method</nolink> ringing. It doesn't seem necessary to further categorise chords into, say, concords and discords.</para>
          <para>Irregular spacing and handstroke gaps are elements of striking. We decided for this first version of the framework only to make a general exhortation on good striking (see the definition of Performance - 3.K.1). We've also included a general ringing quality criterion to the role of umpire(s) in <nolink>record lengths</nolink> -- see 7.B.5. We've added handstroke gaps / cartwheeling, bell spacing and similar topics to the list of items for consideration in a subsequent version of the framework.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="6.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">It's common when reporting <nolink>spliced</nolink>
              <nolink>performances</nolink> to abbreviate Surprise to S, Delight to D, etc. But the framework doesn't cover this. Could it be added?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Agreed and done. See 6.A.2.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="methodextension">
    <title>H. Method Extension</title>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem mrf:label="1.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I could follow most of [Section 13 -- Method Extension Processes] (the diagrams are helpful), but I didn't understand just what a '<nolink>mode</nolink>' was and what it was supposed to mean. It also wasn't clear that the example was Mode=2 from the supplied diagrams. What is the significance of Mode=2, and how is it different from Mode=1 or Mode=6? I understood that Mode has a number between 1 and the Stage (so 6 in this example), but I don't understand what the significance of the selection is. This seems important for the remainder of the criteria and how each section is defined.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Thanks -- helpful feedback. We've now separately defined Mode in the framework (see Appendix D.A.4), and have shown in the further explanation of this section how different <nolink>modes</nolink> affect an example string of place notation.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="2.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Re: Section 8.A: This may be something which could not, or is unlikely to, happen. Is it possible to name a <nolink>method</nolink> on 12 and it therefore becomes the Parent which then potentially precludes the use of the same name for lower numbers, given the current definition?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Good question. Giving a new lower <nolink>stage</nolink>
            <nolink>method</nolink> the same name as an existing higher <nolink>stage</nolink>
            <nolink>method</nolink> isn't precluded provided the <nolink>methods</nolink> are related. E.g. assume XYZ Maximus has been rung and named. If a Major <nolink>method</nolink> is rung, and an <nolink>extension process</nolink> can be applied to the Major <nolink>method</nolink> to obtain XYZ Maximus, then the Major and Maximus <nolink>methods</nolink> are related. The Major <nolink>method</nolink> can therefore be named XYZ Major if all other <nolink>extension</nolink> requirements are met. The term 'parent' doesn't imply that the <nolink>parent method</nolink> was rung and named before any <nolink>extensions</nolink> were rung / named. Parent is just the lower or lowest <nolink>stage</nolink>
            <nolink>method</nolink> in a set of <nolink>related methods</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="typosgrammarlayoutformatting">
    <title>I. Typos / Grammar / Layout / Formatting</title>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem mrf:label="1.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">What is the status of sections 10-14? Reference is made to the <nolink>extensions</nolink> processes, but not the others.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>The previous sections 10-14 are now appendices in the latest version of the framework. As described in Section 1.C, the appendices are supporting material, and are not part of the framework itself.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="2.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Likelihood is misspelled in Section 11, paragraph 1.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Thanks -- fixed.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="3.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I was unsure why section 4.A.5 requires 'in question' at the end.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We felt that just 'a <nolink>block</nolink>' rather than 'a <nolink>block</nolink> in question' was insufficiently specific -- the former could be interpreted as 'any <nolink>block</nolink>'. The same applies to Sections 4.A.6, 4.A.14, 4.A.15 and 4.A.16.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="4.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Section 7.B.5 -- 'be' is missing between 'must' and 'heard'.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Thanks -- fixed.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="5.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">One small inconsistency: 7.C.4 refers to an umpires’ report (thereby precluding a single umpire). 9.D.5 refers to the umpire(s)’ report. 'Report of the umpire(s)' would definitively overcome this.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We've changed 7.C.4 to refer to umpire(s)’ report, consistent with 9.D.5. While we agree 'report of the umpire(s)' better handles both singular and plural instances, we felt that "umpires' report" is part of the <nolink>record length</nolink> vernacular.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="6.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.J.5 What are x and y? (integers, natural numbers, integers &gt;= 0)</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>This is just numbering / labelling. Agree that (x) and (y) could give the impression of representing quantities, so these have now been changed to (i) and (ii) to hopefully make things clearer.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="recordlengths">
    <title>J. Record Lengths</title>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem mrf:label="1.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Re: Section 7.B, Record Lengths: This section requires the organiser to notify the RW and the Central Council of forthcoming attempt. Could this be changed to just 'The RW and CCCBR must be notified', without adding a requirement of who must notify? This simplification would avoid possible non-compliance if the conductor and not the organiser gave the required notices.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Agreed -- thanks. This <nolink>change</nolink> has been made.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="2.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">There is some uncertainty in <nolink>record length</nolink> ringing as to what the umpires should do. Can the framework clarify this?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Agreed. We've now expanded 7.B.5 to include, in general terms, the type of checking the umpire(s) should do. Also, 6.C.2.g states the norm that 'No person not ringing provided any assistance in the execution of the ringing during the Performance, e.g. making <nolink>calls</nolink>, detecting or correcting errors.' This replaces the 'No assistance of any kind' language of the Decisions. This means that if an umpire (or any other person present), say, picks up a ringer's water bottle that has fallen out of the ringer's reach, this is acceptable as it isn't assistance with the execution of the ringing. The same would apply to turning on a light, turning off a heater, etc.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="pealsoftriples-5040changes">
    <title>K. Peals of Triples &lt; 5040 Changes</title>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem mrf:label="1.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">There is an obvious and elegant reason why a <nolink>peal</nolink> of Triples should be 5040 <nolink>changes</nolink>. I think it is illogical and unnecessary to <nolink>change</nolink> this.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>This may be the single most contentious issue that has emerged during the framework project, so here's a longer answer covering this point.</para>
          <para>Clearly there's a strong link between the word '<nolink>peal</nolink>' and the ringing of an <nolink>extent</nolink> of Triples, and in fact in the early days of ringing, <nolink>peal</nolink> was also used to describe the ringing of an <nolink>extent</nolink> of Minor.</para>
          <para>It might have been more elegant if <nolink>peals</nolink> at all <nolink>stages</nolink> had originally been defined as 5040 or more <nolink>changes</nolink>. But <nolink>peals</nolink> of less than 5040 started to be rung for Major and above as early as 1755, and so the 5000 minimum for higher <nolink>stages</nolink> is long established, and dates to well before the Central Council was formed.</para>
          <para>While many people would like to see 5040 retained as the minimum <nolink>length</nolink> for a <nolink>peal</nolink> of Triples, there are many others who support the simpler and more consistent approach of <nolink>peals</nolink> having a minimum <nolink>length</nolink> of 5000 <nolink>changes</nolink> at all <nolink>stages</nolink>. The limited data we have suggests a split of around 60/40, with the majority favoring standardisation on 5000 at all <nolink>stages</nolink>.</para>
          <para>It's important to note that the framework gives ranges for the different <nolink>performance</nolink>
            <nolink>lengths</nolink> -- e.g. a QP is 1250 - 2499, and a <nolink>half peal</nolink> is 2500 - 4999. In this context, a <nolink>peal</nolink> having a range of 5000 - 9999 and being part of a bigger sequence of <nolink>performance</nolink>
            <nolink>lengths</nolink> supports standardisation on a 5000 minimum.</para>
          <para>It’s perhaps also worth noting that the <nolink>length</nolink> of the <nolink>extent</nolink> isn't part of ringing’s <nolink>performance</nolink> terminology anywhere else. For example, a QP of Minor is reasonably close to two <nolink>extents</nolink>, but there wasn’t a move to make 1440 the minimum number of <nolink>changes</nolink> for a Minor QP. This isn’t a directly comparable situation given we recognise that the concept of a <nolink>peal</nolink> originated from the goal of ringing an <nolink>extent</nolink>. But it highlights that we can view standard <nolink>performance</nolink> ranges (&lt;1250, 1250-2499, 2500-4999, 5000-9999, and &gt;=10000) as distinct from <nolink>extent</nolink>
            <nolink>lengths</nolink> (24, 120, 720, 5040) which are single numbers.</para>
          <para>Setting the minimum <nolink>length</nolink> at 5000 for all <nolink>stages</nolink> allows those who want to continue ringing no less than 5040 to do so. But setting the definition at 5040 takes away the option of ringing between 5000 and 5039 from those who want it. Using 5000 is therefore the permissive option. It’s clearly also the simpler option, as a <nolink>peal</nolink> can have the same definition across all <nolink>stages</nolink>.</para>
          <para>There could be a separate carve-out for Triples – i.e. for all <nolink>stages</nolink> except Triples, a <nolink>peal</nolink> requires a minimum of 5000 <nolink>changes</nolink>, but for Triples the minimum is 5040. But this then raises several other questions: should a QP of Triples (the <nolink>length</nolink> that enables a new <nolink>method</nolink> to be named) be 1260 instead of 1250? Is a <nolink>half peal</nolink> of Triples 2520 and a <nolink>long length</nolink> of Triples 10080?</para>
          <para>There could also be valid reasons for wanting to ring 5000-5039 Triples. There might be a wish to ring a <nolink>peal</nolink> in this <nolink>length</nolink> range for an anniversary of the last two numbers (e.g. a 5026 for a 26th birthday) and only a Triples <nolink>band</nolink> is available. There could be an interesting compositional reason for doing so -- e.g. there's a <nolink>true</nolink>, non-round 5039 of Grandsire Triples that only uses bobs. For over two centuries, composers have been searching for a bobs-only <nolink>extent</nolink> of Erin Triples. So far, the longest <nolink>true</nolink> bobs-only <nolink>round block</nolink> found is 4990 <nolink>changes</nolink>. If, say, a 5004 is found (before any longer <nolink>length</nolink>), a number of ringers would be interested in ringing it.</para>
          <para>Even with a move to a standard minimum <nolink>peal</nolink>
            <nolink>length</nolink> of 5000, we can be sure that the vast majority of Triples <nolink>peals</nolink> will continue to be 5040 <nolink>changes</nolink> in <nolink>length</nolink>. There is, of <nolink>course</nolink>, something very elegant and appealing about ringing every possible <nolink>row</nolink> exactly once.</para>
          <para>In 2016, the Decisions were relaxed to allow <nolink>peals</nolink> of Triples (and lower <nolink>stages</nolink>) to include partial <nolink>extents</nolink>. Previously a <nolink>peal</nolink> of Triples could only be whole multiples of <nolink>extents</nolink> (5040, 10080, 15120, etc). Under the current Decisions, they can be any <nolink>length</nolink> that is 5040 or higher. Since that update, 353 <nolink>peals</nolink> of Triples have been posted on BellBoard (at the time of writing). Only one of them took advantage of the Decision <nolink>change</nolink> -- a 5320 of Grandsire Triples -- the rest were all 5040s. The 5320 was an interesting <nolink>performance</nolink> because the <nolink>composition</nolink> was bobs only -- not something that can be done in a 5040 of Grandsire Triples. We have similar expectations that ringers will only choose to ring between 5000 and 5039 of Triples when there is a specific reason for doing so.</para>
          <para>We’ve therefore retained 5000 as the minimum <nolink>length</nolink> for <nolink>peals</nolink> across all <nolink>stages</nolink>. This is the permissive approach, and keeping ringing terminology as simple and consistent as possible makes things easier for new ringers joining the Exercise. No one has to ring a 5000 – 5039 of Triples if they don’t want to, but equally we don't think anyone should try to prevent those who do want to ring a 5000 – 5039 of Triples from claiming a <nolink>peal</nolink>, given this number meets the requirement for a <nolink>peal</nolink> at other <nolink>stages</nolink>. In any community such as ours there will be a wide range of opinions, and ultimately it's beneficial if we can find ways to coexist as peacefully as possible. No one thinks a 4999 should be a <nolink>peal</nolink> (ok, you could probably find someone who thinks this), but there are many ringers who would like to see 5000 as the minimum <nolink>peal</nolink>
            <nolink>length</nolink> across all <nolink>stages</nolink>. The 5040 supporters can still choose never to ring <nolink>peals</nolink> of Triples that are less than 5040 <nolink>changes</nolink>. Live and let live.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="technicalcomments">
    <title>L. Technical Comments</title>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem mrf:label="1.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Check mathematics for formal permutation definitions.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> Also <nolink>cycle</nolink> notation</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> (12)(34)(56)</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> 3.C.1. unfortunately mathematicians seem to regard transposition differently:</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> http://mathworld.wolfram.com/Transposition.html</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> 'For example, the swapping of 2 and 5 to take the list 123456 to 153426 is a transposition'</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We've now added the following technical comment to 3.C.1: 'Note that in mathematics, transposition refers to the exchange of two elements. However in ringing, as well as in more general usage, transposition can involve the exchange of more than two elements. For example, ringers talk about transposing <nolink>coursing</nolink> orders, which often involves rotating 3 bells.'</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="2.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.E.1. 'A sequence of Changes all of the same Stage, or a process to generate such a sequence.'</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> The 'process' part is a little tricky and leaves scope for well defined, but useless definitions.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> E.g. process</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> Ring [1.3.1.3.1.{7|5}.3.1.3.1.3.{7|5}]^840</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> where at each choice of 7 or 5, 7 is chosen unless it is impossible to generate a <nolink>round block</nolink> of the <nolink>extent</nolink> with any choice of following 7 or 5s.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> This exists, but we don't know what it is.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> It is a '<nolink>static method</nolink>'.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> [3.1.3.1.3.{7|5}]^840</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> where at each choice of 7 or 5, 7 is chosen unless it is impossible to generate a <nolink>round block</nolink> of the <nolink>extent</nolink> with any choice of following 7 or 5s.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> This might, or might not exist.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> What is this?</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> [3.1.3.1.3.{7|5}]^840</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> where at each choice of 7 or 5, 7 is chosen unless it is impossible to generate a longer or same <nolink>length</nolink>
              <nolink>round block</nolink> than if 5 is chosen, with any choice of following 7 or 5s.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> This exists, but we don't know how long it is, but it is fixed and finite.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> It is a <nolink>static method</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> Method PI Royal</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> Generate the digits of PI with a decimal expansion</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> 1-&gt;10</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> 2-&gt;12</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> 3-&gt;30</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> 4-&gt;14</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> 5-&gt;50</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> 6-&gt;16</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> 7-&gt;70</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> 8-&gt;18</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> 9-&gt;90</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> 0-&gt;X</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> ignore the first z digits until the remaining 3628800 <nolink>changes</nolink> generates the <nolink>extent</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Agreed that processes for generating sequences of <nolink>changes</nolink> could be well-defined but practically useless, as demonstrated by your examples. We've now added the following technical comment to 3.E.3 (Dynamic Method), that uses your bobs-only Erin example:</para>
          <para>"Technical comment: A Dynamic Method should be capable of producing a readily-determinable sequence of Changes. A process such as 'Ring the Changes [3.1.3.1.3.{7|5}]^840 where at each choice of 7 or 5, 7 is chosen unless it is impossible to generate a Round Block of the Extent with any choice of following 7 or 5s' is not a valid Dynamic Method, even though this is a well-defined process.</para>
          <para>"Dynamic Methods are in their infancy, and more precise definitions in this area may be developed for future versions of the framework if there is sufficient interest by the ringing community."</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="3.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.G.1 "In addition to using a Method's whole sequence of Changes one or more times in a Composition, any subset of a Method's sequence of Changes may also be used."</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> 'Any subset'? including the empty set?</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> Do you mean contiguous chunk, or any random <nolink>changes</nolink> extracted from the <nolink>method</nolink>?</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> What about double bob minimus X14X34X14X12.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> We can take any subset of those <nolink>changes</nolink> multiple times and have any other adjacent-<nolink>change</nolink>
              <nolink>method</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>This is the known problem of overlap -- there isn't a way to define <nolink>method</nolink> ringing such that there is only one valid way to describe any given sequence of <nolink>changes</nolink>. E.g. Stedman can also be described as <nolink>spliced</nolink> Erin and Bastow Little Bob.</para>
          <para>Any attempt to enforce a single way of defining a given sequence of <nolink>changes</nolink> results in valid ringing constructs also being ruled out. We therefore leave it to ringers to use their good judgement in deciding the best way to describe any given sequence of <nolink>changes</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="4.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">2.B.6 Truth at N is every possible <nolink>row</nolink> not more than N times. Complete at N is every possible <nolink>row</nolink> at least N times. then with cover or fixed bells, <nolink>truth</nolink> is still maintained Completeness is all possibly distinct <nolink>rows</nolink> while maintaining fixed bells</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Agreed. Put another way, and replacing N with M in your second sentence, we can say that any <nolink>touch</nolink> can be given a pair of numbers, N and M, relating to its <nolink>truth</nolink>.</para>
          <para>For no <nolink>rows</nolink> repeated, N = 1 (e.g. a normal <nolink>peal</nolink> of Triples of higher);</para>
          <para>For complete, N = M (e.g. two <nolink>extents</nolink> of Grandsire Doubles, where N and M = 2);</para>
          <para>For <nolink>truth</nolink> as defined in the framework, N - M &lt;= 1.</para>
          <para>We found that we didn't need to define Complete for use elsewhere in the framework, though it is a commonly-used term when discussing <nolink>truth</nolink>. We therefore didn't include Complete in the interests of simplicity.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="secondconsultation">
    <title>M. Second Consultation</title>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem mrf:label="1.">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I have nothing to add to the informed and refined Framework for Method Ringing as drafted.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Thank you for this feedback.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="2. a)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Good on the whole and easy to understand (unless you're on a mobile device!)</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Yes, we recognize the framework isn’t easy to read on a mobile device. This is on the list of items to look at for future versions of the framework.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="2. b)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">A couple of comments:</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic"> 4.A.1 mentions <nolink>dynamic methods</nolink> but no further explanation is given. I assume this would cater for the likes of Dixon's Bob Minor? How is this to be classified?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Yes, Dixon’s is a <nolink>dynamic method</nolink> – the only one so far that is reasonably well known. Dynamic methods (with Dixon’s as an example) are defined in 3.E.3. There is no proposed subclassification of <nolink>dynamic methods</nolink> at this <nolink>stage</nolink>, given there are so few of them. We have now added a note to this effect in 4.A.1.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="2. c)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">4.E would be much easier to understand with an example.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Good suggestion – examples have now been added.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="2. d)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Link missing from 5.D.1 + 5.D.2.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Thanks, now updated. The <nolink>calls</nolink> and <nolink>variations</nolink> libraries are not yet provided by the CC (see Appendix F.4). Once they are, links will be added. We’ve now cross referenced Appendix F.4 from 5.D.2.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="2. e)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">5.D.3 how do we classify April Day Triples, i.e. Plain Bob with Grandsire <nolink>calls</nolink>? Is it still Plain Bob?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>A <nolink>variation</nolink> has the same classification as the <nolink>method</nolink> on which it’s based – see 5.D.4 a). So April Day has a Bob classification. But note that <nolink>variations</nolink> are currently only recorded in the library at the Doubles <nolink>stage</nolink> (see 5.D.3). The possibility of expanding the <nolink>variations library</nolink> to record <nolink>variations</nolink> at other <nolink>stages</nolink> is on the list of items for consideration in later versions of the framework.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="2. f)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">5.E.1 b) should also use the word contain, instead of is, when talking about a <nolink>round block</nolink>, eg if a 1440 of Minor is rung during a multi <nolink>method</nolink>
              <nolink>peal</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>In 5.E.1 b), <nolink>round block</nolink> is being used at the <nolink>performance</nolink> level – i.e. the complete <nolink>performance</nolink> is required to be a <nolink>round block</nolink> when naming a new <nolink>method</nolink>. The framework recognises non-<nolink>round block</nolink>
            <nolink>performances</nolink> (since the goal is to be descriptive / permissive) such as ringing that starts in Rounds and ends in Queens. But new <nolink>methods</nolink> have traditionally been named in <nolink>round block</nolink>
            <nolink>performances</nolink>, and the framework maintains this tradition. Note that a <nolink>round block</nolink>
            <nolink>performance</nolink> can comprise many smaller <nolink>round blocks</nolink> – e.g. a <nolink>peal</nolink> of 7 <nolink>round block</nolink>
            <nolink>extents</nolink> of Minor.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="3. a)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">With reference to: "6.B.4 The report of a Performance that used simulated sound must state that it did." This gave rise to a number of questions in my mind, and the more I thought about it the more involved and complicated it got. So I've tried to précis my thoughts</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">1) The Exercise of ringing is about controlling the bell(s). The art of producing a sound is that of the bell-founder -- nothing to do with ringing. So why stipulate the form of sound production? Does it matter if the bells are made of steel, or they are major third bells? If it's to do with people listening to the <nolink>performance</nolink>, would it be OK if the sound was broadcast from PA speakers on the tower?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>The purpose of 6.B.4 is to provide information in <nolink>performance reports</nolink> that some members of the ringing community will want to know about. Some ringers will only want to read about <nolink>performances</nolink> that were rung with real bell sounds – clapper on bell metal. Others will be interested in reading about <nolink>performances</nolink> rung with real bell sounds or simulated sound. 6.B.4 lets readers find what they’re interested in reading about.</para>
          <para>This clause is not related to listening to the <nolink>performance</nolink>. The requirement for tower bells to be audible outside the building has already been removed from the Decisions (removed in 2017).</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="3. b)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">2) Is the problem to do with the possibility that the <nolink>performance</nolink> might be on DUMB BELLS? I recognise that the mechanism may be different, but if you don't differentiate between, say, "mini-rings" and tower bells, why should this be an issue? One still has to control the bell(s).</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We don’t see a need for additional disclosure on dumb bells (or dumb handbells). By definition, these will have simulated sound, which will be disclosed under 6.B.4. The distinction between a <nolink>performance</nolink> rung on dumb bells with simulated sound, and a <nolink>performance</nolink> rung on tower bells whose clappers were tied and using simulated sound, doesn’t seem crucial enough to warrant a specific disclosure. And in practice the distinction will often be clear from other parts of the <nolink>performance report</nolink> – e.g. where the <nolink>performance</nolink> was rung or the weight of the tenor.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="3. c)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3) Perhaps this statement was intended to refer to simulated RINGERS? It seems from what I've read elsewhere in your document that, provided an umpire was present, a single bell, rung by a single person, would be classified as a <nolink>performance</nolink> even if all the other bells were rung by simulated ringers and the <nolink>performance</nolink> otherwise met all other criteria. Is that correct?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>The framework assumes all bells were rung by human ringers. 6.B.1 f) <nolink>calls</nolink> for their names to be included in the <nolink>performance report</nolink>, 6.C.2 e) refers to bells being rung by people, and 6.C.2 h) and i) refer to the human way of ringing bells.</para>
          <para>The single person plus umpire reference relates to (say) one person ringing a <nolink>performance</nolink> of Minimus on handbells with four-in-hand. It doesn’t refer to computers ringing some of the bells.</para>
          <para>The framework therefore doesn’t cover ringing by pressing a key on a keyboard, and/or having a computer ring some of the bells. However, these sorts of <nolink>performances</nolink> are occasionally posted on BellBoard. In these cases 6.C.2 o) applies – the <nolink>performance</nolink> wasn’t consistent with the framework, and therefore under 6.C.1, the <nolink>performance report</nolink> should state what took <nolink>place</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="3. d)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Overall, I rather think that this clause goes against the spirit of your remit. In case it's relevant, I mention the following: I sometimes ring QPs on a simulator at a local ringing centre. When we first did this, the <nolink>performance</nolink> notices stated that they were "Rung on Abel". More recently, they give the name of the tower as the ringing centre, rather than the church. Performances on the open bells are given as rung at the church. Even so, as the bells are muffled and the sound control is in <nolink>place</nolink> when we ring on the simulator, it is still possible to listen to the bells if you stand at the base of the tower -- but traffic noise and natural attenuation is sufficient to make the bells virtually inaudible at the boundary of the graveyard. If the bells had their clappers tied this would be different -- but it would *feel* different to ring, too. What is important here? This needs some thought!</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We hope the comments above cover your points. In summary, the framework covers human ringers ringing full circle (tower bells) or alternating up-strokes and down-strokes (handbells), and if the sound was simulated, this should be disclosed. Use of simulated ringers and/or ringing by pressing a key is outside the framework and this should be disclosed in the <nolink>performance report</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="4. a)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">There are over 300 Slow Course <nolink>methods</nolink> in the CC Library, including nearly 20% of the 187 <nolink>methods</nolink> in the 1980 Doubles Collection. The earliest of these, Itchingfield, dates back to around 1900 and others were first rung in the 1950s. Why should it be necessary to rename these <nolink>methods</nolink>?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We agree it’s not ideal renaming (or retitling) any <nolink>method</nolink>. However, as ringing has evolved over the decades, the classification system has become overcomplicated, and given our ‘simple’ mandate, we believe some limited rationalization is helpful. We’ve deliberately limited the number of <nolink>methods</nolink> that are retitled as a result of our classification <nolink>changes</nolink> to keep this manageable.</para>
          <para>The Slow Course classification is the most anachronistic and inconsistent classification in the Decisions. It’s the only classification that depends on two different classes of <nolink>hunt</nolink>
            <nolink>path</nolink> being present, and it requires a specific bell (the 2nd) to have a certain <nolink>hunt</nolink>
            <nolink>path</nolink>. Retiring Slow Course results in a small but useful reduction in the complexity of the classification system.</para>
          <para>There is also prior precedent for retiring classes that are felt to be no longer needed. E.g. the Imperial, College and Court classifications were retired in 1982.</para>
          <para>It’s planned for the <nolink>methods library</nolink> to store names / titles by which <nolink>methods</nolink> have previously been known, so once this is implemented, it will still be possible to search for Slow Course <nolink>methods</nolink> by their previous names / titles.</para>
          <para>We’re giving <nolink>bands</nolink> that named Slow Course <nolink>methods</nolink> the option to include either ‘Slow’ or ‘Slow Course’ in the <nolink>method name</nolink> if they wish.</para>
          <para>Overall, it’s a close <nolink>call</nolink>, but on balance we think the benefits of making some simplifications to the classification system outweigh the inconvenience of a small percentage of <nolink>methods</nolink> being renamed or retitled.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="4. b)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">The framework attempts to define <nolink>truth</nolink> in a way that it can be applied to any <nolink>performance</nolink> without reference to the <nolink>stage</nolink> of the <nolink>methods</nolink> being rung. Whilst a laudable aim, this can <nolink>lead</nolink> to inconsistencies.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Applying the criteria to the "Effective Stage" of a <nolink>composition</nolink> and not the "Composition Stage" means that e.g. a 240 of Doubles with the tenor behind could be claimed as a <nolink>true</nolink>
              <nolink>touch</nolink> of Minor where the tenor remains in 6th’s <nolink>place</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Our view is that <nolink>truth</nolink> should be assessed on a <nolink>block</nolink> of <nolink>rows</nolink>, regardless of what <nolink>composition</nolink> was used to generate these <nolink>rows</nolink>. It’s well-known that different <nolink>compositions</nolink> can generate the same <nolink>rows</nolink> (e.g. the same <nolink>touch</nolink> of Stedman can be produced by splicing Erin and Bastow Little Bob). In your example, even if the <nolink>composition</nolink> used Minor <nolink>method</nolink>(s), the 240 <nolink>rows</nolink> the <nolink>composition</nolink> generates have an <nolink>effective stage</nolink> of Doubles, so <nolink>truth</nolink> should be assessed at this <nolink>stage</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="4. c)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">"Accepted Truth" is intended to provide an algorithm for the equivalent of the existing decision on <nolink>peals</nolink> of Doubles and Minor, etc, that does not require the individual <nolink>blocks</nolink> to be specified. However, there are several problems with the resultant definition:</emphasis>
          </para>
          <itemizedlist role="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="italic">It includes possibilities not covered by the existing decision (e.g. an <nolink>extent</nolink> of Minor plus partial <nolink>extents</nolink> of both Doubles and Minor);</emphasis>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Accepted truth generated a lot of debate among the framework team. Historically, <nolink>peals</nolink> of, say, 6 <nolink>extents</nolink> of Minor plus 6 <nolink>extents</nolink> of Doubles with a cover have been accepted as <nolink>true</nolink>, even though if these 5040 <nolink>rows</nolink> were all considered at the Minor <nolink>stage</nolink>, the <nolink>performance</nolink> wouldn’t be <nolink>true</nolink>. We’ve therefore adopted the term ‘<nolink>accepted truth</nolink>’ to differentiate the two.</para>
          <para>With this as the starting point, the question is then, do the two <nolink>stages</nolink> have to comprise complete <nolink>extents</nolink>, or can there also be partial <nolink>extents</nolink>? We’re trying to be descriptive and permissive, so the answer is that partial <nolink>extents</nolink> should be recognized if <nolink>bands</nolink> choose to ring them.</para>
          <para>The next question is should there be able to be a partial <nolink>extent</nolink> at both <nolink>stages</nolink>, or only at one <nolink>stage</nolink>. The Decisions required complete <nolink>extents</nolink> up until 2016, but then recognized a partial <nolink>extent</nolink> being rung at one of the two <nolink>stages</nolink> (but not both) from this point onwards.</para>
          <para>In the interests of permissiveness, we started by recognizing partial <nolink>extents</nolink> at both <nolink>stages</nolink>. So, for example, a QP of 900 Minor and 450 Doubles could have <nolink>accepted truth</nolink>. The problem with this approach is that it gives some anomalous results. For example, a 720 of Minor and 2 <nolink>plain courses</nolink> of Stedman Doubles would appear to be false. But one of the <nolink>plain courses</nolink> of Stedman Doubles could be considered to be a partial <nolink>extent</nolink> of Minor, and therefore this <nolink>performance</nolink> could be viewed as 780 Minor and 60 of Doubles, and have <nolink>accepted truth</nolink>. This seemed wrong, so we’ve now updated the definition of <nolink>accepted truth</nolink> to only recognize a partial <nolink>extent</nolink> at one of the two <nolink>stages</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="4. d)">
        <mrf:question>
          <itemizedlist role="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="italic">It excludes possibilities covered by the existing decision (e.g. <nolink>extents</nolink> of Doubles plus a partial <nolink>extent</nolink> of Minor);</emphasis>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>This is intentional. We believe the rationale for <nolink>accepted truth</nolink> is that once you’ve rung all the possible <nolink>rows</nolink> on a given number of bells, there is justification in relaxing the definition of <nolink>truth</nolink> to enable more variety. From the meeting minutes, this seemed to be the intent of the 1898 Central Council debate on <nolink>peals</nolink> of Doubles and Minor. It also explains why the current Decisions don’t recognize, for example, an <nolink>extent</nolink> of Triples and a partial <nolink>extent</nolink> of Major.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="4. e)">
        <mrf:question>
          <itemizedlist role="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="italic">It excludes <nolink>touches</nolink> that are True according to the more general definition (e.g. a 1440 of Minor ending with 56.56);</emphasis>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Agreed, and this has now been updated. The definition of Accepted Truth now includes anything that is True.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="4. f)">
        <mrf:question>
          <itemizedlist role="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="italic">It does not address additional possibilities covered by the more permissive aspects of the framework, e.g. multiple <nolink>cover bells</nolink> or a <nolink>cover bell</nolink> leading.</emphasis>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>This is also intentional. Performances of Doubles and Minor, etc have had a specific structure for many decades, and we don’t see a case, at least in version 1 of the framework, for changing this.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="4. g)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">If we fully embrace the Descriptive, Permissive mandate, then I believe that the Accepted Truth definition is unnecessary. Instead, we only require that what is rung is accurately reported. The Performance Norms should be either of:</emphasis>
          </para>
          <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha" role="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="italic">The <nolink>performance</nolink> consists of a single True <nolink>composition</nolink>, and the report should make clear both the <nolink>length</nolink> and (if there are any <nolink>cover bells</nolink>) which bells take part in the <nolink>composition</nolink>;</emphasis>
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="italic">The <nolink>performance</nolink> consists of a series of separate True <nolink>compositions</nolink>, each reported as in a). If these are followed, it should be clear whether or not a <nolink>peal</nolink> complies with the existing decisions regarding <nolink>truth</nolink>, and so unnecessary to state that it does not.</emphasis>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We think it should be possible to determine <nolink>truth</nolink> just by inspecting the <nolink>rows</nolink> that were rung. No knowledge of the underlying <nolink>compositions</nolink> should be needed to determine <nolink>truth</nolink>. E.g. if two false <nolink>compositions</nolink> are rung back to back, but together they produce a <nolink>true</nolink> set of <nolink>rows</nolink>, the <nolink>performance</nolink> should be <nolink>true</nolink>.</para>
          <para>If <nolink>compositions</nolink> are performed side by side (e.g. on 12 bells, a Minor <nolink>composition</nolink> is rung on the front 6 and another Minor <nolink>composition</nolink> is rung on the back 6), <nolink>truth</nolink> should be assessed at the Maximus <nolink>stage</nolink>. The <nolink>truth</nolink> of the individual <nolink>compositions</nolink> isn’t relevant in this scenario.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="4. h)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.E.1 of the framework defines a Method as "A sequence of Changes all of the same Stage, or a process to generate such a sequence". This dichotomy has bothered me from when it was first proposed. The notes make it clear that a “sequence” refers to a single lead, and could be a building <nolink>block</nolink> for a <nolink>composition</nolink>, or an entry in a <nolink>methods library</nolink> - but this does not capture the essence of a <nolink>method</nolink>, that it repeats indefinitely, and there is always a next <nolink>change</nolink>. A “process” is better, and could be applied to either a Static Method or a Dynamic Method. However, there is no indication of any restriction on what the process can be, or how it might be recorded: Are two processes that generate the same sequence the same Method? Is the process "Plain Hunt except 2nd’s is made when the treble leads" the same as Plain Bob? Does a process have to be deterministic? Is "if it is Sunday, ring Grandsire, otherwise ring Stedman" a <nolink>method</nolink>?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We agree a <nolink>method</nolink> is hard to define rigorously, and if we were to use a fully rigorous definition, it would probably be very technical and not much use to “ordinary ringers”. We’ve therefore applied a common-sense definition for version 1 of the framework. The benefit of defining a <nolink>method</nolink> in terms of a single <nolink>plain lead</nolink> is that this corresponds to what is recorded in the <nolink>methods library</nolink>.</para>
          <para>Our definition also allows for <nolink>methods</nolink> such as Dixon’s, where the sequence of <nolink>changes</nolink> isn’t fixed, but since such <nolink>dynamic methods</nolink> are only rung very rarely at present, we haven’t attempted to develop fully precise definitions in this area. We also haven’t tried to determine what restrictions (if any) should be applied to the processes underlying <nolink>dynamic methods</nolink>, nor specify how <nolink>dynamic methods</nolink> should be recorded in the <nolink>methods library</nolink>. These areas can all be considered in future versions of the framework if there’s sufficient interest by the ringing community.</para>
          <para>Your statement “there is always a next <nolink>change</nolink>” is potentially problematic. While a <nolink>static method</nolink>’s <nolink>changes</nolink> can be thought of as repeating indefinitely, a <nolink>dynamic method</nolink> could be created where, under a given condition, the sequence of <nolink>changes</nolink> ends.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="5. a)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">"5.C.8: A Method should only be given the same Name as another Method in the Methods Library that has a different Stage if the requirements for Method Extension are met.”</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I used to think that Class Descriptors each represented a 'name space' such that names could be re-used at will provided the Class Descriptor was different. From the wording here (including the use of 'should') it seems to be more complicated. But if for example I wish to name a new Triples <nolink>principle</nolink> 'Danbury', I'd like to believe that would be OK, without having to read all the material about Method Extension just because there are already similarly named Delight and Treble Place methods at a different <nolink>stage</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>That’s correct – the Class Descriptor represents a namespace and <nolink>method names</nolink> can generally be reused within each namespace, as is the case under the Decisions. But see the example in 8.B.3 for an exception. Applying this exception to your example, you’re generally free to name your Triples <nolink>principle</nolink> Danbury even though there may already be Danbury Delight and Danbury Treble Place methods. However, if a Doubles <nolink>principle</nolink> has already been named Danbury, you can only name your Triples <nolink>principle</nolink> Danbury if it’s related to Danbury Doubles. Similarly, if Danbury Caters and Danbury Cinques have already been named, you can only name your Triples <nolink>principle</nolink> Danbury if it’s on the same <nolink>extension path</nolink> as the Caters and Cinques <nolink>methods</nolink>.</para>
          <para>There’s no particular significance to the use of ‘should’. These are requirements of the framework but we wanted to avoid authoritarian language such as ‘must’ or ‘shall’.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="5. b)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">8.A.1 Further explanation: The Central Council's collection of recognised Extension Processes can be found in Appendix B.” It's in Appendix D. "</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Thank you – now fixed.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="6. a)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I'd like to make 2 points on the current draft of the framework:</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.H.2 states "A Composition is described as Variable Cover if one or more Cover Bells are affected by any of the Composition's Calls." However, in dual-<nolink>stage</nolink>
              <nolink>peals</nolink>, <nolink>quarter peals</nolink>, etc. there may be only one bell which covers for the part(s) of the <nolink>composition</nolink> with a <nolink>cover bell</nolink>, but this bell is affected by <nolink>calls</nolink> (even if the <nolink>call</nolink> is simply the <nolink>change</nolink> of <nolink>method</nolink>). I would not describe this <nolink>composition</nolink> as '<nolink>variable cover</nolink>' but under this current draft it could be described as such. (Perhaps that is intended, and dual-<nolink>stage</nolink>
              <nolink>performances</nolink> will be considered as <nolink>variable cover</nolink>, but I do not feel that they are currently viewed as such.)</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Thank you – we agree the example you describe shouldn’t be <nolink>variable cover</nolink>. We’ve now added the following to the further explanation of 3.H.2: “Note that a Composition is not considered Variable Cover if a Cover Bell is only affected by a <nolink>change</nolink> to a higher Stage Method such that the (former) Cover Bell is now one of the bells on which the Method's Changes operate.”</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="6. b)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">6.B.1 and 7.B.2 both make reference to the date on which a <nolink>performance</nolink> takes <nolink>place</nolink>. There have been a handful of - often notable - <nolink>performances</nolink> in history which have taken <nolink>place</nolink> on more than one day e.g. 40320 Plain Bob Major on 27th-28th July 1963. I therefore suggest that "date" is replaced with "date(s)" in 6.B.1 and "date" is replaced with "start date" in 7.B.2</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>On 7.B.2 (notice of <nolink>record lengths</nolink>), we agree the notification should say start date (as opposed to just date) – this has now been updated.</para>
          <para>On 6.B.1 (content of <nolink>performance reports</nolink>), we did consider multiple dates, but since a goal is for <nolink>performance reports</nolink> to be easily stored in databases, we felt a single date field was preferable, given how infrequently <nolink>performances</nolink> span midnight. We’ve already stated in the further explanation for 6.B.1 that the date to use in the report is the date on which the <nolink>performance</nolink> ended. We’ve now added a sentence to the 6.B.1 further explanation suggesting that <nolink>bands</nolink> may wish to include the <nolink>performance</nolink> start date in the footnote if it’s different from the end date (and in this case, perhaps also the start or end time).</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="7. a)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">7. Record Lengths:</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Q1: These currently go through the Peals team in the History &amp; Archive Workgroup. Is it anticipated that the e-mailing of notices and reports will be continued by that team as an activity that is shared with the Technical workgroup?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Yes. The Technical &amp; Taxonomy Workgroup is happy to assist with any activities related to Record Lengths, but the activity and associated processes are currently the responsibility of the History &amp; Archive Workgroup. The Framework has now been updated in this regard as this section was drafted when Peal Records Committee work was expected to fall in the Technical &amp; Taxonomy remit. The Further Explanation sections in 7.B and 7.C now say “… can be emailed to the Central Council's History &amp; Archive Workgroup at records@cccbr.org.uk.”</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="7. b)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Q2: There is a final step in the current process where, the reports being assessed as being satisfactory, the RW Editor is informed that it is OK to publish the <nolink>performance</nolink>. Is it intended that this should continue?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Yes, this step is covered in Section 9.D.4. A further explanation has now been added stating that the CC’s History &amp; Archive workgroup performs this step.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="7. c)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">9. Related Roles - E. Analysis and Reporting:</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Q1: Is it expected that the Peals team in the History &amp; Archive Workgroup will continue to use their experience and skills to fulfil this requirement?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Yes, this is our understanding. The Technical &amp; Taxonomy Workgroup is happy to assist as requested. For example, it can help with the list of <nolink>methods</nolink> first rung during the year, noting that <nolink>methods</nolink> may be first rung in <nolink>extents</nolink> and <nolink>quarter peals</nolink> as well as <nolink>peals</nolink>, so all these should be included.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="7. d)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Q2: How will the publishing of the report be managed?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Similarly, we understand that this is the responsibility of the History &amp; Archive Workgroup. The Technical &amp; Taxonomy Workgroup would be happy to help compile the report and/or review it for consistency and accuracy.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="7. e)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Q3: What is the purpose and audience of the reporting? If it is intended to inform Council debate and decisions, a calendar year report would be of reduced relevance due to the lateness of the CCCBR meeting. If it is for the wider edification of the ringing community then perhaps some thought needs to go into the content, scope and functionality that would be expected in a modern digital world.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We believe that such reporting should be for the benefit of the Ringing Exercise as a whole as well as to inform Central Council initiatives, and would agree that it is beneficial to provide selected analysis online not just for the current year, but also for historic years.</para>
          <para>We deliberately have not stated in detail the form or content of such reporting to allow flexibility and continuous improvement. The Technical &amp; Taxonomy Workgroup would be happy to work with the History &amp; Archive Workgroup and The Ringing World on improving and automating procedures for compiling, maintaining and presenting the analysis, from which a report to the Council can also be created with sufficient currency for the AGM.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="7. f)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Appendix F. Transitional Arrangements - 2. Retroactive recognition of Peals:</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Q1: Is it expected that the Peals team in the History &amp; Archive Workgroup will continue to use their experience and skills to fulfil this requirement?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Yes. The Framework has now been updated in this regard as this section was drafted when Peal Records Committee work was expected to fall in the Technical &amp; Taxonomy remit. The words 'T&amp;T Workgroup' have been amended to 'History &amp; Archive Workgroup' and the email address to 'records@cccbr.org.uk'.</para>
          <para>Adding such <nolink>peals</nolink> retroactively should be similar to the approach taken for early <nolink>peals</nolink> identified from newspapers that are missing from the records. In this case, it may save effort to undertake a review of annual Central Council Reports for <nolink>peals</nolink> excluded from each analysis, and update the historic records accordingly - determining an appropriate <nolink>course</nolink> of action for any <nolink>methods</nolink> that have not been subsequently added to the CCCBR Methods Library.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8. a)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I have number of fundamental objections to the framework as it is now presented and do not feel any of the points I have made previously have been adequately addressed.</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">The framework does not meet the criteria specified by the Council, specifically it is not simple and does not use the simple straightforward language of real ringing; if the Council had asked for framework for the theory behind bellringing it would be more acceptable but it does not describe the real world of practical ringing.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>The framework isn’t attempting only to describe practical, everyday ringing. There are other publications that do this. It’s attempting to be a framework that can describe all forms of <nolink>method</nolink> ringing. But this includes describing many forms of ‘real ringing’ that aren’t covered by the Decisions, such as <nolink>quarter peals</nolink>, and ringing with more than one <nolink>cover bell</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8. b)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Also, too many terms are redefined to completely <nolink>change</nolink> their historic meanings, this is particularly <nolink>true</nolink> of the meaning of the term `<nolink>method</nolink>' which is now defined to be something quite indeterminate, whereas historically it has always been a <nolink>round block</nolink> divisible into equal parts called leads. While the previous decisions of the Council had a number of serious flaws I do believe that, in many ways, they were nearer to what is required than the current theoretical approach which, in my opinion, is also fundamentally flawed.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>The framework recognises a <nolink>method</nolink> that has one lead in its <nolink>plain course</nolink>, whereas the Decisions require a <nolink>method</nolink> to have 2 or more leads. The Decisions treat a one-lead <nolink>method</nolink> as a non-<nolink>method</nolink>
            <nolink>block</nolink>. The concept of non-<nolink>method</nolink>
            <nolink>blocks</nolink> has been widely criticized, and was a large impetus behind the CC vote in 2014 to undertake a fundamental review of the Decisions.</para>
          <para>The topic of <nolink>methods</nolink> with one-lead <nolink>plain courses</nolink> was debated extensively by the Ringing Theory email group in 2014. A poll was taken to gauge views. 35 people responded to the poll and 80% supported <nolink>methods</nolink> being able to have a one-lead <nolink>plain course</nolink>.</para>
          <para>Take the minor <nolink>method</nolink> 34.16x34x16.34.12. It has 5 leads in its <nolink>plain course</nolink>. If the last <nolink>change</nolink> is altered to give 34.16x34x16.34.16, the <nolink>method</nolink> now has 1 lead in its <nolink>plain course</nolink>. We don’t see there is any justification or logic in saying that altering one place notation results in us no longer being engaged in <nolink>method</nolink> ringing.</para>
          <para>In light of the above, and since there are only 7 non-<nolink>method</nolink>
            <nolink>blocks</nolink> in the <nolink>methods library</nolink> today (note the illogicality of including non-<nolink>methods</nolink> in a <nolink>methods library</nolink>), in the interests of simplicity we have eliminated non-<nolink>method</nolink>
            <nolink>blocks</nolink> and treated one-lead <nolink>methods</nolink> as <nolink>methods</nolink>.</para>
          <para>There is a valid argument that <nolink>methods</nolink> with one-lead <nolink>plain courses</nolink> should be separately classified. We debated this and it was a close <nolink>call</nolink>, but we decided in the end that it was unnecessary to add a new classification for these <nolink>methods</nolink>. The classification system is already overly-complicated and we should be trying to simplify it rather than adding new classes. And if you rang, say, Bristol Surprise Major with a 12 <nolink>lead end</nolink>, this would still seem like ringing a <nolink>surprise method</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8. c)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I think the committee has been disingenuous in not making clear the wide-ranging <nolink>changes</nolink> to terminology they are proposing in their comments in The Ringing World and so the rank and file ringer has been unaware of the nature of what is being proposed.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We think this is unfair. We’ve gone out of our way to be fully transparent at all <nolink>stages</nolink> of this project. The live draft of the framework has been publicly available on the Internet since Oct 2017, with the URL published in all 4 of our RW articles. Our second RW article (Mar 2nd 2018) outlined all the main <nolink>changes</nolink> in the new framework, including that <nolink>methods</nolink> with one-lead <nolink>plain courses</nolink> would be recognised.</para>
          <para>We’ve held two ringing-community-wide consultations. The second of these was publicized very widely, including in the RW, on ringers’ email lists, on Facebook and Twitter, on the CC website, and by communication to all CC members and to all CC-affiliated societies. It’s hard to know what else we could have done to be more open about the nature of what we’re proposing. No one else has accused us of disingenuity.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8. d)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">As I have said previously I think what is needed is a precise description of <nolink>change</nolink>-ringing and that the definition of a <nolink>method</nolink> should not be expanded in the way it is to makes it all-encompassing but again almost meaningless as it becomes virtually the same as a lead or a <nolink>block</nolink> and so totally opaque to the normal ringer.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>There is no practical way of limiting the definition of a <nolink>method</nolink> so that only nonsensical cases are excluded – this always results in sensible cases also being ruled out. Arbitrary limits on a <nolink>method</nolink> will annoy ringers who believe the limits have been set in the wrong <nolink>place</nolink>, as we’ve seen over the past 100 years. It’s better to remove the limits and let ringers decide what they wish to name as <nolink>methods</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8. e)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I believe we are fundamentally <nolink>change</nolink> ringers and not <nolink>method</nolink> ringers and this is borne out by the fact that many Associations have `Change Ringers' in their title and none as far as I know have `Method Ringers'.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We view <nolink>change</nolink> ringing as encompassing both <nolink>method</nolink> ringing and <nolink>call</nolink>
            <nolink>change</nolink> ringing, and since most associations support both, it makes sense for them to describe themselves as <nolink>change</nolink> ringing organizations. This subject was debated on the Ringing Theory list in 2015 and a poll was held. 77% supported the view that the difference between <nolink>method</nolink> ringing and <nolink>change</nolink> ringing is that the latter also includes <nolink>call</nolink>
            <nolink>change</nolink> ringing.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8. f)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">As examples of things that aren't <nolink>methods</nolink> but are perfectly acceptable pieces of ringing, Dixon's Bob Minor fell foul of the previous regulations because of the insistence that <nolink>peals</nolink> had to consist of <nolink>methods</nolink> and the <nolink>methods</nolink> had to conform to the decisions; the present framework invents a new category of <nolink>method</nolink> rather than describing what it is: a rule-based way of generating <nolink>changes</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>All <nolink>methods</nolink> are rules (or processes) for generating <nolink>rows</nolink>. The rules may be simple (a fixed string of <nolink>changes</nolink>) or complex (the <nolink>changes</nolink> vary depending on other criteria), but the level of complexity shouldn’t be used to prevent certain <nolink>methods</nolink> from being <nolink>methods</nolink>. We believe most people ringing Dixon’s would consider themselves to be ringing ‘a funny kind of <nolink>method</nolink>’ as opposed to not ringing a <nolink>method</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8. g)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">It is also easy to generate a <nolink>true</nolink>
              <nolink>block</nolink> of 24 <nolink>changes</nolink> of minimus which has no structure and if it were to be divided into `<nolink>methods</nolink>' the choice would be pretty arbitrary; why does this have to be called a <nolink>method</nolink> when it is simply a <nolink>round block</nolink>; all successful ringing should be <nolink>round blocks</nolink> and there should be no necessity for them to contain leads or <nolink>methods</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>A <nolink>band</nolink> that rings such a <nolink>true</nolink>
            <nolink>block</nolink> would normally want to record it in the <nolink>methods library</nolink>. It makes sense for the <nolink>methods library</nolink> to house <nolink>methods</nolink>, as opposed to other things.</para>
          <para>There is a valid argument for detaching <nolink>methods</nolink> from <nolink>peals</nolink>, etc, and we’ve debated this (as has the Ringing Theory group). The consensus is that detachment leads to unnecessary complexity. There is valuable simplicity in using <nolink>methods</nolink> (together with <nolink>calls</nolink> and <nolink>cover bells</nolink>) as the building <nolink>blocks</nolink> for all <nolink>performances</nolink>.</para>
          <para>We also shouldn’t (and haven’t in the framework) stipulate that all successful ringing should be <nolink>round blocks</nolink> – that’s prescription not description. If a <nolink>band</nolink> chooses to ring a non-<nolink>round block</nolink> (such as the bobs-only 5039 Grandsire Triples), the only requirement is that they disclose in the report that the <nolink>performance</nolink> wasn’t a <nolink>round block</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8. h)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">We need honesty in ringing and if you ring a <nolink>round block</nolink> of 24 <nolink>changes</nolink>
              <nolink>call</nolink> it that, it can have a name if you want but it's a <nolink>round block</nolink> not a <nolink>method</nolink>, a <nolink>method</nolink> is simply a special case of a <nolink>round block</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>As before, naming it means adding it to the <nolink>methods library</nolink>, which, logic dictates, should contain <nolink>methods</nolink>. And most ringers ringing a <nolink>round block</nolink> of 24 <nolink>changes</nolink> would think of themselves as ringing a <nolink>method</nolink>, having learnt the <nolink>method</nolink>’s blue line, etc.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8. i)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">A few specific points:</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Rows: This definition has no connection with actual ringing and might be suitable from a compositional point of view, but not a practical ringing perspective. A definition such as `A <nolink>row</nolink> is a sequence in which each of the participating bells rings once, and only once, all at the same stroke.' According to the definition given there no reference to where this sequence may occur so 531 at handstroke followed by 246 at backstroke would be a <nolink>row</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>This is intentional. We’re trying to be descriptive, not prescriptive. If a <nolink>band</nolink> wants to ring <nolink>rows</nolink> with odd-numbered bells on one stroke and even-numbered bells on the other stroke, we’re not trying to prevent them. The current Decisions also don’t preclude this.</para>
          <para>However, your comment has brought to light that we don’t have a disclosure requirement for such ringing. We’ve therefore added an item to the Performance Norms section (6.C.2) asking for disclosure if every <nolink>row</nolink> in a <nolink>performance</nolink> didn’t have all the bells ringing at the same stroke.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8. j)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Rounds: The numbers refer to pitch so why not say `A Row in which the bells are ordered from the highest pitch to the lowest pitch'</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>It’s explained in the definition for Row that bells are numbered according to pitch. Given this, it seems better not to refer to pitch again in the definition of Rounds, but instead to refer to the now-established numbering of bells. Rounds is usually depicted in writing using bell numbers.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8. k)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Rounds also means the repeated ringing of this <nolink>row</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Yes, this term has more than one use, as do many ringing terms. Ringing <nolink>rounds</nolink> is outside the scope of <nolink>method</nolink> ringing, so we don’t think the framework needs to refer to <nolink>rounds</nolink> ringing per se. The definition of True shows how opening <nolink>rounds</nolink> and closing <nolink>rounds</nolink> traditionally bookend a <nolink>method</nolink> ringing <nolink>performance</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8. l)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Change: Again the definition has no real connection with practical ringing. Most ringers would understand that a <nolink>change</nolink> is the transition from ringing in one order to a different order. Thus the definition of a <nolink>change</nolink> should be something similar to 'A Change is the transition from ringing one <nolink>row</nolink> to a different one at the next stroke'. The <nolink>identity change</nolink> is a purely mathematical concept, and alien to practical ringing where it is known as a repeated <nolink>row</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>This isn’t correct. E.g., <nolink>touches</nolink> of Doubles are sometimes rung using a Single with place notation 12345. This <nolink>call</nolink> can be used to turn a 120 of Doubles into a 240 where every possible <nolink>row</nolink> appears twice, once at handstroke and once at backstroke. Experience has shown that most of the time, ringers don’t notice the same <nolink>row</nolink> has been rung twice in succession, and they don’t think that they weren’t engaged in <nolink>method</nolink> ringing. The <nolink>identity change</nolink> clearly affects <nolink>truth</nolink>, but nothing more. And again, we want to be descriptive not prescriptive -- if <nolink>bands</nolink> choose to ring the <nolink>identity change</nolink>, we want the framework to have terminology that can describe this.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8. m)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">The definition `<nolink>adjacent change</nolink>' is a made-up one which will be confusing to many people as it could easily be mistaken for adjacent <nolink>rows</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We expect most ringers will continue to use the existing term ‘<nolink>change</nolink>’ in relation to everyday ringing, and that’s by design – we don’t want to impose new terms on ringers unnecessarily (nor would we succeed). Using the more precise terms of <nolink>adjacent change</nolink>, <nolink>identity change</nolink> and <nolink>jump change</nolink> (which are the three sub-categories of <nolink>change</nolink>) will only be needed in more advanced situations.</para>
          <para>Also, the Decisions and the framework both use the term ‘consecutive’ when referring to adjacent <nolink>rows</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8. n)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">I don't think it necessary but think the basic rules for normal <nolink>change</nolink> ringing should be included (note this does not preclude other types of ringing but defines a normal standard)</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>There will never be agreement on where to draw the dividing line for normal. 100 years of CC Decisions experience shows this.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8. o)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Each bell rings once and only one in each <nolink>row</nolink>. In <nolink>changes</nolink> no bell may move more than one <nolink>place</nolink> at a time.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>This rules out <nolink>jump changes</nolink>. If <nolink>bands</nolink> choose to ring <nolink>jump changes</nolink>, as occasionally they do, we want the framework to be able to describe this. For those who don’t want to read about such <nolink>performances</nolink>, the framework ensures <nolink>performance reports</nolink> make clear when <nolink>jump changes</nolink> were used so that readers can ignore these <nolink>performances</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8. p)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">Methods and Blocks: I think the definitions are wrong and completely <nolink>change</nolink> the accepted meanings of several of these terms. A Block is a general term of a series of more than one <nolink>changes</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>That’s only one of the uses of <nolink>block</nolink>. E.g. <nolink>round block</nolink> refers to <nolink>rows</nolink>. We’ve noted in 3.D.1 that <nolink>block</nolink> has more than one meaning, and the framework’s use of <nolink>block</nolink> isn’t intended to preclude any other use.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8. q)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">There are several types of <nolink>block</nolink>, for instance a <nolink>round block</nolink>, a lead, a division, a part of a <nolink>peal</nolink>
              <nolink>composition</nolink>. The definition of a <nolink>method</nolink> as a sequence of <nolink>changes</nolink> all at the same <nolink>stage</nolink> could be anything;</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>This is by design. There’s no practical way to limit the definition of a <nolink>method</nolink> that doesn’t also rule out sensible cases.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="8. r)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">The characteristics of a <nolink>method</nolink> are (i) it is a <nolink>round block</nolink> of <nolink>changes</nolink>, (ii) it is divisible in to equal parts and (iii) it does not contain any <nolink>calls</nolink>. Your definition does not meet any of these criteria so is clearly wrong. I will say no more as I think the whole framework needs to total rethink to reconnect with the historic definitions of <nolink>change</nolink> ringing and not simply coin a series of terms, which may be relevant to the theory of ringing, but really have no relevance to the normal ringing done in our bell towers.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <orderedlist numeration="lowerroman" role="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>All fixed sequences of <nolink>changes</nolink> will produce a <nolink>round block</nolink> if the sequence is rung enough times. The framework defines a <nolink>plain course</nolink> of a <nolink>method</nolink> in this way. The framework defines a <nolink>method</nolink> in terms of a <nolink>plain lead</nolink> rather than a <nolink>plain course</nolink>. This is to give consistency with what appears in the <nolink>methods library</nolink> for each <nolink>method</nolink> (the place notation for a <nolink>plain lead</nolink>).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>As noted above, we don’t see any justification for preventing a <nolink>method</nolink> with a one-lead <nolink>plain course</nolink> from being a <nolink>method</nolink>. The alternative treatments are worse.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>We agree a <nolink>method</nolink> doesn’t contain any <nolink>calls</nolink>. The definition of a <nolink>call</nolink> makes clear that a <nolink>call</nolink> modifies a <nolink>method</nolink>, so it should be clear that a <nolink>method</nolink> by itself doesn’t contain any <nolink>calls</nolink>. Making this point explicitly would <nolink>lead</nolink> to circular definitions (the definition of <nolink>method</nolink> would use ‘<nolink>call</nolink>’ and the definition of <nolink>call</nolink> would use ‘<nolink>method</nolink>’), which we’ve tried to avoid for obvious reasons. However, we note that the current Decisions say in the definition of a <nolink>call</nolink> that a <nolink>call</nolink> is not part of the definition of a <nolink>method</nolink>, and we don’t have this in the framework. We’ve therefore now added this to our definition of <nolink>call</nolink>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. a)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.B.1. As phrased, this appears to imply that a Row may be missing one or more bells. If this is not the intention why the “no more than once” language rather than a more explicit “in which each bell appears exactly once”?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>The problem is that ‘each’ would be undefined – e.g. each bell in England? See FAQ B.27.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. b)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.E.5. As worded 7,007 consecutive Plain Leads of Cambridge Major is a Plain Course (it’s an application of the <nolink>method</nolink>’s sequence of <nolink>change</nolink> repeatedly, and is a <nolink>round block</nolink>). I doubt that this is intended. If it is intended, then I think all <nolink>methods</nolink> have a countably infinite set of different <nolink>plain courses</nolink>, which would seem surprising.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>The definition says ‘… until a Round Block is obtained’, meaning the first occurrence of a <nolink>round block</nolink>, which occurs after 7 <nolink>plain leads</nolink>. We don’t believe this wording will cause any confusion.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. c)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.E.5. I wonder if it should be made explicit that the whole of the <nolink>method</nolink>’s sequence of <nolink>changes</nolink> should be applied at each repetition? You could have a <nolink>method</nolink> that comes round in the middle of what is commonly considered it’s <nolink>plain course</nolink>, and that is arguably “apply its sequence of <nolink>changes</nolink> repeatedly until a <nolink>round block</nolink> is obtained.” I think this could be fixed by say something like “applying all of a <nolink>static method</nolink>’s sequence of <nolink>changes</nolink>” or something like that.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>This is covered in the technical comments. In general, we’ve tried to keep edge case complexity out of the main definitions.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. d)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.F.1. The strict wording of this seems a bit ambiguous, as in normal conversation “replace X with different X” might well be construed to imply at least one X thingie is being replaced by at least one different X thingie. Making it explicit with “zero or more <nolink>changes</nolink>” in both <nolink>places</nolink> might be worthwhile. Yes, the Further explanation does make this clear, but section 1.C implies the further explanations are not normative.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We did have “zero or more” language in this definition at one <nolink>stage</nolink>, but took it out on the basis that it was overly-technical (which we’ve been criticized for). In general, we’ve attempted to keep the definitions as straightforward as possible, and use the further explanations to add clarity where needed.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. e)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.F.2. Is there a “<nolink>calls library</nolink>” yet?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Not yet. 3.F.2 has now been updated to refer to Appendix F.4, which explains this.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. f)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.G.1 and 3.G.2. I don’t think, as currently worded, this works as desired. Consider two consecutive standard <nolink>extents</nolink>, one of Cambridge Minor and one of London Minor. I believe the intention of 3.G.2 is that this not be considered <nolink>spliced</nolink>. However, the wording of 3.G.1 certainly allows this to be a single <nolink>composition</nolink> of <nolink>length</nolink> 1,440, which is <nolink>spliced</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Even if your two standard Minor <nolink>extents</nolink> are considered to be a single <nolink>composition</nolink> of 1440 <nolink>changes</nolink>, the <nolink>change</nolink> of <nolink>method</nolink> occurs at <nolink>rounds</nolink> (or more precisely, the same <nolink>row</nolink> as the initial <nolink>row</nolink>). The 1440 <nolink>composition</nolink> is therefore not <nolink>spliced</nolink>.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. g)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.H.2. Consider the little minor <nolink>method</nolink> with place notation 5.1.5.3.5.3x4x6. Now consider a <nolink>touch</nolink> of it <nolink>spliced</nolink> with a doubles <nolink>method</nolink>, with <nolink>half lead changes</nolink> of <nolink>method</nolink> in the minor, where only the first half-lead of the minor <nolink>method</nolink> is ever rung. Does not 3.H.2. describe this as “<nolink>variable cover</nolink>” since the <nolink>changes</nolink> of <nolink>method</nolink> do, in <nolink>principle</nolink>, affect the tenor, even though in the end it never leaves 6ths <nolink>place</nolink>?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Agreed. We’ve now added the following further explanation: “Note that a Composition is not considered Variable Cover if a Cover Bell is only affected by a <nolink>change</nolink> to a higher Stage Method such that the (former) Cover Bell is now one of the bells on which the Method's Changes operate.”</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. h)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.J.1. The further explanation contradicts the definitions: it says <nolink>methods</nolink> and <nolink>compositions</nolink> can be <nolink>extents</nolink>, but that is not possible — an <nolink>extent</nolink> is a set of <nolink>rows</nolink>, while <nolink>methods</nolink> and <nolink>compositions</nolink> are sets of <nolink>changes</nolink>. Note that this is not about order, which is the point the further explanation is trying to make, it is about what are the constituent bits of the sets/sequences under consideration.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>The further explanation doesn’t say that a <nolink>method</nolink> or <nolink>composition</nolink> can be an <nolink>extent</nolink> – as you say, <nolink>methods</nolink> and <nolink>compositions</nolink> are sequences of <nolink>changes</nolink>, whereas an <nolink>extent</nolink> is a set of <nolink>rows</nolink>. The explanation says, “… when used with a Method or Composition (e.g. an Extent of Plain Bob Minor), this generally refers to an ordered Extent generated using the Changes of Plain Bob Minor (and any necessary Calls).” I.e. “used with a Method or Composition”, not “is a Method or Composition”.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. i)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.J.3. The technical comment should say “the <nolink>effective stage</nolink> of a <nolink>block</nolink> all of whose <nolink>rows</nolink> are the same” — a <nolink>block</nolink> can’t be comprised of just <nolink>rows</nolink>, as it is explicitly defined as a composite of both <nolink>changes</nolink> and <nolink>rows</nolink>.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Agreed – updated.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. j)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">3.J.4, second sentence. Consider a <nolink>method</nolink>, the last <nolink>change</nolink> of whose <nolink>plain lead</nolink> is an <nolink>identity change</nolink>. By splicing this with another weird <nolink>method</nolink> you could easily come up with a “<nolink>true</nolink>,” in the colloquial sense, MEB in two different ways, one including the last <nolink>row</nolink> and one excluding it. It’s making my head hurt trying to figure out exactly how this relates to this the second sentence of 3.J.4, but I suspect it may not be quite what is intended or desirable.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We think this works as is. In your example, the <nolink>composition</nolink> will determine whether the last <nolink>row</nolink> is included or excluded. Truth is then determined from the <nolink>block</nolink> produced by the <nolink>composition</nolink> (including consideration of whether or not the <nolink>block</nolink> is round).</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. k)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">4.D.1. It seems odd that the triples <nolink>method</nolink> 1.127 is classified as plain, but 1.127,125 is not; in fact, the latter <nolink>method</nolink> has no classification.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We've revisited how <nolink>stationary bells</nolink> are classified, and in the end decided to make them all Treble Place, regardless of lead <nolink>length</nolink>. There's nothing 'plain' about a <nolink>method</nolink> with a <nolink>stationary bell</nolink>, and Treble Place seems the most fitting class for these (Treble is a proxy for <nolink>hunt bell</nolink>, and Place, as in 'making <nolink>places</nolink>', is what a <nolink>stationary bell</nolink> does).</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. l)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">4.D.6. It seems odd that you can’t have a Little Jump method. For example, it is pretty obvious how to construct Cunning Little Vixen Little Treble Jump Major, is it not? Or maybe we just let the name of that be “Cunning Little Vixen Little Treble”? I guess with Jump stuff being so unexplored it makes sense to leave things as simple as possible, but it might be worth a note or something, I dunno.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We’ve had lots of debate on this topic. For now, <nolink>hunters</nolink> that have <nolink>jump changes</nolink> are classified as Hunters in the classification diagram in 4.A.1, but are not members of any of the sub-classes below Hunter. They are also members of the Jump class. But as you say, there may be a case for enabling <nolink>hunters</nolink> with <nolink>jump changes</nolink> be part of other <nolink>hunter</nolink> sub-classes (e.g. X Jump Surprise Major, Y Jump Little Treble Bob Royal), as well as possibly adding a sub-class where the <nolink>hunt bell</nolink> jumps (e.g. Cambridge Treble Jump Minor). This is on the list to be revisited in a subsequent version of the framework, and we've now included a note in the <nolink>hunter</nolink> sub-class explanations indicating this.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. m)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">5.A.1 Further explanation: the link is rather oddly structured: the whole sentence “The Methods Library can be accessed here” is blue and looks like a link, but it is only a word “here” that is a link — for a long time I thought there was no link at all, and only stumbled over the last word being a link accidentally, so I suspect it will confuse others, too.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Agreed. It's a little garish, but for now we've made all framework hyperlinks green. To be revisited in a subsequent version of the framework.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. n)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">5.A.1 More on the link: it is odd that the page is headed “Compositions Library,” when what you believe you’ve been directed to is the “Central Council Methods Library.” In fact, those verbatim words do not appear anywhere on the page that is the target of the link.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Agreed. We’ve now changed this link to https://<nolink>methods</nolink>.cccbr.org.uk.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. o)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">5.B.1 A strict reading of “The Class Descriptor is formed by concatenating…” would appear to imply that the <nolink>class descriptor</nolink> of, say, a little <nolink>surprise method</nolink>, is “LittleSurprise” rather than “Little Surprise”. Things are concatenated with spaces added as necessary. And, of <nolink>course</nolink>, when adding something that’s blank, no additional space is added.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>That’s the computing use of concatenate. We think the more general dictionary definition “linked together” makes clear what is intended here.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. p)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">5.C.2 and similar sections: it would be nice if these cross references to appendices were links.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Agreed. However, there are over 100 cross references in the framework and we thought it would be too difficult to manage all these as manual hyperlinks. This is on the list to revisit in a subsequent version of the framework, ideally finding a way to automate the management of cross reference hyperlinks.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. q)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">5.C.3 should “would result in its Method Title being the same” instead be “would result in their Method Titles being the same”?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Agreed – updated.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. r)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">5.D.1 it seems surprising that the Further explanation points at the Methods Library rather than the Variations Library. Perhaps some redistribution of the further explanations of this section and following is warranted?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Agreed, the <nolink>methods library</nolink> reference was included in 5.D.1 in error. Now updated.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. s)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">5.D.2 Is there a Variations Library yet? Or a Calls library?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Not yet. 5.D.2 has now been updated to refer to Appendix F.4, which explains this.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. t)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">5.D.3 Further explanation. When it says “At Stages other than Doubles, Method Names are independent of the Call or Calls used.” While this was mandated in the past (and I see no reason to <nolink>change</nolink> it), it does *not* appear to be mandated in this framework. Again, a further explanation does not appear to be considered normative according to 1.C. If this is to be a requirement, it needs to be stated somewhere else, I think. And if it is a requirement, “currently only records Doubles Variations” seems an odd way to phrase it, since there are no other kinds.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We’ve flagged the question of <nolink>variations</nolink> at higher <nolink>stages</nolink> for future consideration. There are many <nolink>performances</nolink> of April Day Triples on BellBoard, and also one of April Day Caters, and perhaps these should be recorded in the Variations Library. Hence why we used “currently” in 5.D.3. But in light of your comment, the further explanation for 5.D.3 doesn’t add anything particularly useful, so we’ve now removed it.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. u)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">5.E.2 In the FAQ (C.1.) it states that you can indeed have <nolink>variations</nolink> that cannot be rung to an <nolink>extent</nolink>, but need an MEB. But this section appears to prohibit naming such a <nolink>variation</nolink>, as it requires an <nolink>extent</nolink> to name it. Something’s fishy.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>5.E.2 only requires the naming <nolink>performance</nolink> to contain an <nolink>extent</nolink> of the new <nolink>variation</nolink> – i.e. all <nolink>rows</nolink> of the <nolink>extent</nolink> occurring somewhere in the <nolink>performance</nolink>. This could be achieved through a single <nolink>extent</nolink>
            <nolink>rounds</nolink>
            <nolink>block</nolink>, but also through an MEB (multi-<nolink>extent</nolink>
            <nolink>block</nolink>).</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. v)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">6.A.1 and 6.A.2 These sections seem to be trying to have it both ways. The normative text is loose, yet the further explanations seem to be trying to say something normative. This doesn’t seem right. If what the further explanation states really is required, it needs to be stated in the definitions, right?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Technically you’re probably correct, but this is an area where we thought we needed to take a pragmatic approach. We consider the further explanations to be ‘best practice’ guides on how to report <nolink>performances</nolink>. Ultimately ringers and The Ringing World will decide how to report <nolink>performances</nolink>, so it seems of limited effect for the framework to try and mandate a set of requirements in this area.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. w)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">6.A.1 further explanation b)4. This is wholly new, right? Presumably it only applied to new reports? Is there a reason for adding this, which has never been viewed as necessary in the past?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We included Mixed as an optional term because so many <nolink>performances</nolink> are reported on BellBoard as Mixed.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. x)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">7.A.2 You may recall that some years ago Rod Pipe (I think it was he) tried to arrange an <nolink>extent</nolink> of Plain Bob Caters, to be rung by several teams of ringers in relays. It never came off, but if it did now, this section states that it would not be considered a <nolink>record length</nolink>. That seems a shame.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We think it’s important for records to be broken under a consistent set of conditions. It wouldn’t be fair to the <nolink>band</nolink> that rang (not in relay) the existing <nolink>record length</nolink> of Plain Bob Caters if their record could be broken by a relay <nolink>performance</nolink> where each individual ringer may ring fewer <nolink>changes</nolink> than in the existing record. There may be a case for a separate category of records for relay <nolink>performances</nolink>, but we think this can be considered in a subsequent version of the framework, or be considered if such a <nolink>performance</nolink> is rung.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. y)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">8.A.1, further explanation: the list of recognized <nolink>extension processes</nolink> is actually appendix D, not appendix B as stated here.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Thanks – now corrected.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. z)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">8.A.1 further explanation: “in the case of a <nolink>static method</nolink>, the structure of the <nolink>method</nolink> is its place notation”. This seems overly constricting. While certainly the blessed <nolink>extension</nolink> stuff of the CCCBR-past has always been place notation based, it would seem plausible that even for <nolink>static methods</nolink> a different sort of scheme might be adopted in the future. I don’t have anything specific in mind, but it seems one of those areas where clever people in the future could push boundaries, and we don’t want to impede them needlessly.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Perhaps, though it’s difficult to imagine a <nolink>method</nolink> that falls within the definition of a <nolink>static method</nolink> not having a structure that can be represented using place notation. Since the new Central Council governing structure will enable the framework to be updated more efficiently than was possible with the previous Decisions, we believe your point here can be addressed effectively in the future if a problem arises.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. aa)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">8.C.1 further explanation. Some sections point folks at <nolink>methods</nolink>@cccbr.org.uk, and others at technical@cccbr.org.uk. Is this deliberate? If so, what is the algorithm for deciding what goes to which? Would not a single entry point be a better approach, even if someone then has to route requests as appropriate?</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>We’ve now settled on the following two email addresses for the framework: <nolink>methods</nolink>@cccbr.org.uk and records@cccbr.org.uk. The reason for having two email addresses is to separate responses based upon the relevant function – <nolink>methods</nolink> or records. Under the new CC structure, enquiries to <nolink>methods</nolink>@cccbr.org.uk will be handled by the Technical and Taxonomy workgroup, and enquiries to records@cccbr.org.uk will be handled by the History and Archive workgroup. However, this separation would be useful even if these functions were in the same workgroup.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
      <listitem mrf:label="9. ab)">
        <mrf:question>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="italic">And, finally, just re-iterating something I wrote to Tim a month ago: I am gob-smacked at how well this turned out. As I think you know, I was skeptical, but at this point I’m really impressed. I may have hoped for something shorter, but that hope really wasn’t practical, and I think the result really is a huge improvement and will serve the future well. I think you folks have done a great job. Thank you!</emphasis>
          </para>
        </mrf:question>
        <mrf:answer mrf:separator="hr">
          <para>Thanks – much appreciated.</para>
        </mrf:answer>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</article>
