<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mrf="https://cccbr.org.uk/ns/method-ringing-framework" version="5.0" xml:id="index-v1" xml:lang="en" mrf:status="historic" mrf:authority="CCCBR" mrf:framework-version="1" mrf:edition-label="Edition 1">
  <info>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <subtitle>Framework for Method Ringing, Section 1</subtitle>
    <edition>1</edition>
    <releaseinfo role="status">historic</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="authority">CCCBR</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="implementation-date">February 24, 2019</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="effective-date">June 1, 2019</releaseinfo>
    <uri type="canonical">https://cccbr.org.uk/index.html</uri>
    <othermeta role="source-path">version1/index.html</othermeta>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="background">
    <title>A. Background</title>
    <para>This website houses the Central Council's framework for <nolink>method</nolink> ringing ('the framework' or 'FMR').</para>
    <para>The framework provides common language and terminology for describing many aspects of <nolink>method</nolink> ringing, and it also contains the Central Council's requirements for adding new <nolink>methods</nolink> to the Central Council's <nolink>methods library</nolink>, for classifying and extending <nolink>methods</nolink>, and for <nolink>record length</nolink>
      <nolink>performances</nolink>. The framework is provided to support effective communication within the ringing community, and its use by all is strongly encouraged.</para>
    <para>The framework is a Standard (a type of Policy under the Central Council's rules). It is mandatory for anything included in the CC's various collections and records (<nolink>methods</nolink>, <nolink>variations</nolink>, <nolink>calls</nolink>, <nolink>extension processes</nolink>, <nolink>record lengths</nolink>), including how things are recorded, classified, analysed and reported. The framework is implemented by the Central Council's Executive.</para>
    <para>This version of the framework was implemented by the Executive on Sunday February 24th 2019, with an effective date of Saturday June 1st 2019.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="material">
    <title>B. Material</title>
    <para>This website contains both (1) the framework, and (2) supporting material that assists in the understanding of the framework, expands upon certain definitions and requirements in the framework, and further assists ringers in communicating about <nolink>method</nolink> ringing.</para>
    <para>The top level parts of Sections 1 to 9 of this website are the framework. 'Top level' means the parts of these sections excluding the expanded material that displays when the '+' buttons are pressed. The appendices of this website, as well as the expanded parts of Sections 1 to 9, are supporting material. The supporting material is updated by the Central Council's Executive when the need arises.</para>
    <para>Method ringing terms that are defined in the framework are capitalised wherever they are used elsewhere in the framework.</para>
    <para>A hardcopy version of the framework is available <link xlink:href="images/index/framework-for-method-ringing-v1.00.pdf">here</link>, and a hardcopy version of the appendices is available <link xlink:href="images/index/framework-for-method-ringing-appendices-v1.00.pdf">here</link> (both in pdf format).</para>
    <note role="further-explanation">
      <para>The framework and supporting material are maintained by the Central Council's Technical &amp; Taxonomy Workgroup.</para>
    </note>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="overview">
    <title>C. Overview of the Framework</title>
    <para>Section 3 provides definitions of core <nolink>method</nolink> ringing terms that are used to describe <nolink>methods</nolink>, <nolink>compositions</nolink> and <nolink>performances</nolink>. The further explanation in Section 3.D.1 includes a diagram that shows how various core terms relate to one another. The framework doesn't attempt to define all terms related to <nolink>method</nolink> ringing -- for this, see the glossary of ringing terms at <link xlink:href="http://jaharrison.me.uk/Ringing/Glossary">http://jaharrison.me.uk/Ringing/Glossary</link>.</para>
    <para>Section 4 describes how <nolink>methods</nolink> are classified (i.e. grouped according to common features). The further explanation in Section 4.A.1 links to a diagram that shows the various classes and sub-classes of <nolink>method</nolink>.</para>
    <para>Section 5 contains the requirements for naming new <nolink>methods</nolink> and recording them in the Central Council's Methods Library.</para>
    <para>Section 6 gives best practices for reporting <nolink>method</nolink> ringing <nolink>performances</nolink> (notably reporting in The Ringing World and on BellBoard).</para>
    <para>Section 7 states the requirements for a <nolink>performance</nolink> to be added to the Central Council's register of <nolink>record lengths</nolink>.</para>
    <para>Section 8 describes how <nolink>methods</nolink> at different <nolink>stages</nolink> can be related to one another, and thus may be eligible to share the same <nolink>method name</nolink>.</para>
    <para>Section 9 describes functions performed by the Central Council and The Ringing World related to the framework.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="development">
    <title>D. Development</title>
    <para>For information on how the framework was developed, and the design <nolink>principles</nolink> that were employed, please see Appendix E.</para>
  </section>
</article>
